<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <text lang="en">
        <body>
            <div1 n="3" type="book" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <lb ed="Bekker" n="6"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="1"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>There are three
                    things which require special attention in regard to speech: first, the sources
                    of proofs; secondly, style; and thirdly, the arrangement of the parts of the
                    speech. We have already spoken of proofs and stated that they are three in
                    number, what is their nature, and why there are only three; for in all cases
                    persuasion is the result either of the judges themselves being affected in a
                    certain manner, or because they consider the speakers to be of a certain
                    character, or because something has been demonstrated. We have also stated the
                    sources from which enthymemes should be derived—some of them being
                    special, the others general commonplaces.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="2"/>We have therefore next to speak of style; for it
                    is not sufficient to know what one ought to say, but one must also know how to
                    say it, and this largely contributes to making the speech appear of a certain
                    character.<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>In the first place, following the
                    natural order, we investigated that which first presented itself—what
                    gives things themselves their persuasiveness;<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>in the
                    second place, their arrangement by style; and in the third place, delivery,
                    which is of the greatest importance but has not yet been treated of by anyone.
                    In fact, it only made its appearance late in tragedy and rhapsody, for at first
                    the poets themselves acted their tragedies.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                        Since the authors of tragedies acted their own plays, there was no need for
                        professional actors, nor for instruction in the art of delivery or acting.
                        This explains why no attempt had been made to deal with the question.
                        Similarly, the rhapsodists (reciters of epic poems) were
                        at first as a rule the composers of the poems themselves.
                    </note> It is
                    clear, therefore, that there is something of the sort in rhetoric as well as in
                    poetry, and it has been dealt with by Glaucon of <placeName key="perseus,Teos"
                                                                                authname="perseus,Teos">Teos
                    </placeName> among others.<milestone unit="section" n="4"/>Now
                    delivery is a matter of voice, as to the mode in which it should be used for
                    each particular emotion; when it should be loud, when low, when intermediate;
                    and how the tones, that is, shrill, deep, and intermediate, should be used; and
                    what rhythms are adapted to each subject. For there are three qualities that are
                    considered,—volume, harmony, rhythm. Those who use these properly
                    nearly always carry off the prizes in dramatic contests, and as at the present
                    day actors have greater influence on the stage than the poets, it is the same In
                    political<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">In the law courts and public
                        assembly.
                    </note> contests, owing to the corruptness of our forms of
                    government.<milestone unit="section" n="5"/>But no treatise has yet been
                    composed on delivery, since the matter of style itself only lately came into
                    notice;
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1404a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>and rightly considered
                    it is thought vulgar.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Cope prefers:
                        “is thought vulgar, and rightly so considered.”
                    </note>
                    But since the whole business of Rhetoric is to influence opinion,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes"
                                                                                           place="unspecified">Or, “is
                        concerned with
                        appearance.”
                    </note> we must pay attention to it, not as being
                    right, but necessary; for, as a matter of right, one should aim at nothing more
                    in a speech than how to avoid exciting pain or pleasure. For justice should
                    consist in fighting the case with the facts alone, so that everything else that
                    is beside demonstration is superfluous; nevertheless, as we have just said, it
                    is of great importance owing to the corruption of the hearer.<milestone unit="section" n="6"/>
                    However, in every system of instruction there is some
                    slight necessity to pay attention to style; for it does make a difference, for
                    the purpose of making a thing clear, to speak in this or that manner; still, the
                    difference is not so very great, but all these things<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes"
                                                                               place="unspecified">i.e. style, delivery,
                        and acting, which are of no use to
                        serious students.
                    </note> are mere outward show for pleasing the hearer;
                    wherefore no one teaches geometry in this way.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="7"/>Now, when delivery comes into fashion, it will
                    have the same effect as acting. Some writers have attempted to say a few words
                    about it, as Thrasymachus, in his
                    <title>Eleoi</title>
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">A treatise on Pathos.</note>; and in fact, a
                    gift for acting
                    is a natural talent and depends less upon art, but in regard to style it is
                    artificial. Wherefore people who excel in this in their turn obtain prizes, just
                    as orators who excel in delivery; for written speeches owe their effect not so
                    much to the sense as to the style.
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="8"/>The poets, as was natural, were the first to
                    give an impulse to style; for words are imitations, and the voice also, which of
                    all our parts is best adapted for imitation, was ready to hand; thus the arts of
                    the rhapsodists, actors, and others, were fashioned.<milestone unit="section" n="9"/>And as the
                    poets, although their utterances were devoid of sense,
                    appeared to have gained their reputation through their style, it was a poetical
                    style that first came into being, as that of Gorgias.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Of Leontini in <placeName key="tgn,7003122"
                                                                                                     authname="tgn,7003122">
                        Sicily</placeName>, Greek sophist and rhetorician (see
                        Introduction).
                    </note>
                    Even now the majority of the uneducated think
                    that such persons express themselves most beautifully, whereas this is not the
                    case, for the style of prose is not the same as that of poetry. And the result
                    proves it; for even the writers of tragedies do not employ it in the same
                    manner, but as they have changed from the tetrametric to the iambic meter,
                    because the latter, of all other meters, most nearly resembles prose, they have
                    in like manner discarded all such words as differ from those of ordinary
                    conversation, with which the early poets used to adorn their writings, and which
                    even now are employed by the writers of hexameters. It is therefore ridiculous
                    to imitate those who no longer employ that manner of writing.<milestone unit="section" n="10"/>
                    Consequently, it is evident that we need not enter
                    too precisely into all questions of style, but only those which concern such a
                    style as we are discussing. As for the other kind of style,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">i.e. the poetic style. See <bibl
                            n="Aristot. Poet. 1458a" default="NO" valid="yes">Aristot. Poet. 22</bibl>, where the choice
                        of words and the extent to
                        which out-of-the-way words and phrases may be used in poetry is
                        discussed.
                    </note>
                    it has already been treated in the
                    <title>Poetics.</title>
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1404b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="2"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>Let this
                    suffice for the consideration of these points. In regard to style, one of its
                    chief merits may be defined as perspicuity. This is shown by the fact that the
                    speech, if it does not make the meaning clear, will not perform its proper
                    function; neither must it be mean, nor above the dignity of the subject, but
                    appropriate to it; for the poetic style may be is not mean, but it is not
                    appropriate to prose.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>Of nouns and verbs it is
                    the proper ones that make style perspicuous
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">“Nouns and verbs” is a conventional
                        expression for all
                        the parts of speech. Cp.
                        <bibl n="Hor. Ars 240" default="NO" valid="yes">Hor. AP 240</bibl>
                        “non ego inornata et dominantia nomina solum verbaque,”
                        where <emph>dominantia</emph> is a literal adaptation of <foreign lang="greek">κύρια</foreign>,
                        the usual Latin equivalent for which is
                        <emph>propria.</emph>
                    </note>
                    ; all the others which have been spoken of
                    in the
                    <title>Poetics</title>
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1457a" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Aristot. Poet. 21</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    elevate and make
                    it ornate; for departure from the ordinary makes it appear more dignified. In
                    this respect men feel the same in regard to style as in regard to foreigners and
                    fellow-citizens.<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>Wherefore we should give our
                    language a “foreign
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">It is impossible
                        to find a satisfactory English equivalent for the terms <foreign lang="greek">ξένος, ξενικός, τὸ
                            ξενίζον</foreign>, as applied to
                        style. “Foreign” does not really convey the idea, which
                        is rather that of something opposed to
                        “home-like,”—out-of-the-way, as if from
                        “abroad.” Jebb suggests
                        “distinctive.”
                    </note>
                    air”; for men admire
                    what is remote, and that which excites admiration is pleasant. In poetry many
                    things conduce to this and there it is appropriate; for the subjects and persons
                    spoken of are more out of the common. But in prose such methods are appropriate
                    in much fewer instances, for the subject is less elevated; and even in poetry,
                    if fine language were used by a slave or a very young man, or about quite
                    unimportant matters, it would be hardly becoming; for even here due proportion
                    consists in contraction and amplification as the subject requires.<milestone unit="section" n="4"/>
                    Wherefore those who practise this artifice must
                    conceal it and avoid the appearance of speaking artificially instead of
                    naturally; for that which is natural persuades,<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>but the
                    artificial does not. For men become suspicious of one whom they think to be
                    laying a trap for them, as they are of mixed wines. Such was the case with the
                    voice of Theodorus as contrasted with that of the rest of the actors; for his
                    seemed to be the voice of the speaker, that of the others the voice of someone
                    else.<milestone unit="section" n="5"/>Art is cleverly concealed when the
                    speaker chooses his words from ordinary language
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Cp. <bibl n="Hor. Ars 46" default="NO"
                                                                                     valid="yes">Hor. AP. 46</bibl>,
                        where it is
                        said that the choice and use of words requires subtlety and care, skill in
                        making an old word new by clever combination (<emph>callida
                            iunctura</emph>) being especially praised.
                    </note>
                    and puts them
                    together like Euripides, who was the first to show the way.
                </p>
                <p>Nouns and verbs being the components of speech, and nouns being of the different
                    kinds which have been considered in the <title>Poetics</title>, of these we
                    should use strange, compound, or coined words only rarely and in few places. We
                    will state later<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Chaps. 3 and 7.</note> in
                    what places they should be used;<milestone unit="section" n="6"/>the reason for
                    this has already been mentioned, namely, that it involves too great a departure
                    from suitable language. Proper and appropriate words and metaphors are alone to
                    be employed in the style of prose; this is shown by the fact that no one employs
                    anything but these. For all use metaphors in conversation, as well as proper and
                    appropriate words; wherefore it is clear that, if a speaker manages well, there
                    will be some thing “foreign” about his speech, while
                    possibly the art may not be detected, and his meaning will be clear. And this,
                    as we have said, is the chief merit of rhetorical language.<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>(In
                    regard to nouns, homonyms are most useful
                    to the sophist, for it is by their aid that he employs captious arguments, and
                    synonyms to the poet.
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1405a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>Instances of words that are both proper and synonymous are
                    “going” and “walking”: for these two
                    words are proper and have the same meaning.)
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">This is a parenthetical note.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It has already been stated, as we have said, in the <title>Poetics</title>,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1457a" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Aristot. Poet.
                        21, 22</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    what each of these things<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The different kinds
                        of words.
                    </note> is, how many kinds of
                    metaphor there are, and that it is most important both in poetry and in prose.
                    <milestone unit="section" n="8"/>But the orator must devote the greater
                    attention to them in prose, since the latter has fewer resources than verse. It
                    is metaphor above all that gives perspicuity, pleasure, and a foreign air, and
                    it cannot be learnt from anyone else;
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1458b" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Aristot. Poet. 22.9</bibl>:
                        “for this
                        alone cannot be borrowed from another.”
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="9"/>but we must make use of metaphors and epithets
                    that are appropriate. This will be secured by observing due proportion;
                    otherwise there will be a lack of propriety, because it is when placed in
                    juxtaposition that contraries are most evident. We must consider, as a red cloak
                    suits a young man, what suits an old one;<milestone unit="section" n="10"/>for
                    the same garment is not suitable for both. And if we wish to ornament our
                    subject, we must derive our metaphor from the better species under the same
                    genus; if to depreciate it, from the worse. Thus, to say (for you have
                    two opposites belonging to the same genus) that the man who begs prays,
                    or that the man who prays begs (for both are forms of
                    asking)<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Begging (as a
                        beggar does) and praying (as a priest might) are
                        both forms of asking, and by substituting one for the other, you can amplify
                        or depreciate.
                    </note> is an instance of doing this; as, when Iphicrates<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes"
                                                                                   place="unspecified">See 1.7.32.
                    </note> called Callias
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Head of a distinguished Athenian family which
                        held the office of torch-bearer at the Eleusinian mysteries. A man of
                        notoriously dissipated character, he took some part in politics.
                    </note>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>a mendicant priest instead of a torch-bearer, Callias
                    replied that Iphicrates himself could not be initiated, otherwise he would not
                    have called him mendicant priest but torch-bearer
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The <foreign lang="greek">δᾳδοῦχος</foreign> or
                        hereditary
                        torch-bearer ranked next to the hierophant or chief priest. In addition to
                        holding the torch during the sacrifices, he took part in the recitation of
                        the ritual and certain purificatory ceremonies. The <foreign lang="greek">μητραγύρται</foreign> or
                        mendicant priests collected alms on behalf of
                        various deities, especially the great Mother Cybele (whence their
                        name). They included both men and women of profligate character,
                        addicted to every kind of lewdness.
                    </note>
                    ; both titles indeed have to do
                    with a divinity, but the one is honorable, the other dishonorable. And some call
                    actors flatterers of Dionysus, whereas they call themselves
                    “artists.” Both these names are metaphors, but the one is a
                    term of abuse, the other the contrary. Similarly, pirates now call themselves
                    purveyors
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Cf.
                        “‘convey’ the wise it call”
                        (<title>Merry Wives,</title> I. iii.). Either the
                        euphemistic or unfavorable application of the term may be adopted.
                    </note>
                    ;
                    and so it is allowable to say that the man who has committed a crime has
                    “made a mistake,” that the man who has “made a
                    mistake” is “guilty of crime”, and that one who
                    has committed a theft has either “taken” or
                    “ravaged.” The saying in the <title>Telephus</title> of
                    Euripides,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Ruling over the oar and having landed in <placeName key="tgn,7016748"
                                                                                   authname="tgn,7016748">
                                Mysia</placeName>,
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    is inappropriate, because the word ruling exceeds the dignity of the
                    subject, and so the artifice can be seen.<milestone unit="section" n="11"/>Forms of words also are
                    faulty, if they do not express an agreeable sound; for
                    instance, Dionysius the Brazen
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">According to
                        <bibl n="Ath. 16.669" default="NO" valid="yes">Athenaeus, p. 669</bibl>, he was a poet
                        and rhetorician who recommended the Athenians to use bronze money.
                    </note>
                    in
                    his elegiacs speaks of poetry as
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="eleg" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>the scream of Calliope;</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    both are sounds, but the metaphor is bad, because the sounds have no
                    meaning.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">A scream is neither articulate
                        nor agreeable, like the sound of poetry, although both are voices or sound,
                        and to that extent the metaphor is correct.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="12"/>Further, metaphors must not be far-fetched, but
                    we must give names to things that have none by deriving the metaphor from what
                    is akin and of the same kind, so that, as soon as it is uttered, it is clearly
                    seen to be akin,
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1405b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>as in the
                    famous enigma,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>I saw a man who glued bronze with fire upon another.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    There was no name for what took place, but as in both cases there is a
                    kind of application, he called the application of the cupping-glass gluing.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Ath. 10.452" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Athenaeus, p.
                        452</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    And, generally speaking, clever enigmas furnish good
                    metaphors; for metaphor is a kind of enigma, so that it is clear that the
                    transference is clever.<milestone unit="section" n="13"/>Metaphors should also
                    be derived from things that are beautiful, the beauty of a word consisting, as
                    Licymnius says, in its sound or sense, and its ugliness in the same. There is a
                    third condition, which refutes the sophistical argument; for it is not the case,
                    as Bryson
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Rhetorician and sophist of
                        <placeName key="tgn,7008299" authname="tgn,7008299">Heraclea</placeName>
                        in <placeName key="tgn,7016619" authname="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>.
                    </note>
                    said, that no one ever uses
                    foul language, if the meaning is the same whether this or that word is used;
                    this is false; for one word is more proper than another, more of a likeness, and
                    better suited to putting the matter before the eyes. Further, this word or that
                    does not signify a thing under the same conditions; thus for this reason also it
                    must be admitted that one word is fairer or fouler than the other. Both, indeed,
                    signify what is fair or foul, but not <emph>qua</emph> fair or foul; or if they
                    do, it is in a greater or less degree. Metaphors therefore should be derived
                    from what is beautiful either in sound, or in signification, or to sight, or to
                    some other sense. For it does make a difference, for instance, whether one says
                    “rosy-fingered morn,” rather than
                    “purple-fingered,”<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>or, what is
                    still worse, “red-fingered.”
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="14"/>As for epithets, they may be applied from what
                    is vile or disgraceful, for instance, “the matricide,” or
                    from what is more honorable, for instance, “the avenger of his
                    father.”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Eur. Orest. 1588" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Eur. Orest. 1588</bibl>. In
                        the preceding line
                        Menelaus accuses Orestes as a matricide and ready to heap murder on murder,
                        to which Orestes replies, you should rather call me the avenger of my father
                        Agamemnon, who had been murdered by his wife Clytaemnestra, the mother of
                        Orestes. “Matricide” and “avenger of his
                        father” show the good and bad sides of the deed of Orestes.
                    </note>
                    When the winner in a mule-race offered Simonides a small sum, he refused to
                    write an ode, as if he thought it beneath him to write on half-asses; but when
                    he gave him a sufficient amount, he wrote,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="lyric" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Hail, daughters of storm-footed steeds!
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Frag. 7 (<title>P.L.G.</title> 3,
                                    p.
                                    39O). The winner of the mule race was Anaxilaus of
                                    <placeName key="tgn,7004296" authname="tgn,7004296">Rhegium</placeName>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    and yet they were also the daughters of asses. Further, the use of
                    diminutives amounts to the same.<milestone unit="section" n="15"/>It is the
                    diminutive which makes the good and the bad appear less, as Aristophanes in the
                    <title>Babylonians</title>
                    jestingly uses “goldlet, cloaklet,
                    affrontlet, diseaselet” instead of “gold, cloak, affront,
                    disease.” But one must be careful to observe the due mean in their use
                    as well as in that of epithets.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="3"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>Frigidity of
                    style arises from four causes: first, the use of compound words, as when
                    Lycophron
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">A sophist, not the poet
                        (author of the obscure <title>Alexander</title> or
                        <title>Cassandra</title>), who was later than Aristotle.
                    </note>
                    speaks of the “many-faced sky of the mighty-topped earth,”
                    “narrow-passaged shore”; and Gorgias of “a
                    begging-poet flatterer,”
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1406a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>“those who commit perjury and those who swear right
                    solemnly.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Lobeck conjectured <foreign lang="greek">
                        κατεπιορκήσαντας</foreign>, “who commit
                        out-and-out perjury.”
                    </note>
                    ” And as Alcidamas says,
                    “the soul full of anger and the face fire-colored,”
                    “he thought that their zeal would be end-accomplishing,”
                    “he made persuasive words end-accomplishing,” and
                    “the azure-colored floor of the sea,” for all these appear
                    poetical because they are compound.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="2"/>This is one cause of frigidity; another is the
                    use of strange words; as Lycophron calls Xerxes “a monster of a
                    man,” Sciron “a human scourge
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Sciron and Sinnis were both robbers slain by
                        Theseus, by
                        Lycophron turns Sinnis into a <foreign lang="greek">γλῶττα</foreign>, using
                        it adjectivally = “destructive”; cf. <foreign lang="greek">σῖνος</foreign>, “harm”; <foreign
                                lang="greek">σίντης
                        </foreign> = <foreign lang="greek">σίννις</foreign>.
                    </note>
                    ”; and Alcidamas says
                    “plaything in poetry,” “the audaciousness of
                    nature,” “whetted with unmitigated wrath of
                    thought.”
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="3"/>A third cause is the use of epithets that are
                    either long or unseasonable or too crowded; thus, in poetry it is appropriate to
                    speak of white milk, but in prose it is less so; and if epithets are employed to
                    excess, they reveal the art and make it evident that it is poetry. And yet such
                    may be used to a certain extent, since it removes the style from the ordinary
                    and gives a “foreign” air. But one must aim at the mean, for
                    neglect to do so does more harm than speaking at random; for a random style
                    lacks merit, but excess is vicious. That is why the style of Alcidamas appears
                    frigid; for he uses epithets not as a seasoning but as a regular dish, so
                    crowded,<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>so long, and so glaring are they. For
                    instance, he does not say “sweat” but “damp
                    sweat”; not “to the Isthmian games” but
                    “to the solemn assembly of the Isthmian games”; not
                    “laws”, but “the laws, the rulers of
                    states”; not “running”, but “with a
                    race-like impulse of the soul”; not “museum”, but
                    “having taken up the museum of nature”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The meaning of <foreign lang="greek">
                        παραλαβών
                    </foreign> is
                        quite obscure: various renderings are “having taken to
                        himself,” “received,”
                        “grasped,” “inherited.” The word
                        <foreign lang="greek">μουσεῖον</foreign>, originally a haunt of the
                        Muses, came to mean a school of art or literature. The fault appears to
                        consist in the addition of <foreign lang="greek">τῆς φύσεως</foreign>, but
                        it is difficult to see why. Cope confesses his inability to understand the
                        passage. Jebb translates: “he does not say, ‘having
                        taken to himself a school of the Muses,’ but ‘to
                        <emph>Nature's</emph>
                        school of the Muses.’”
                    </note>
                    ;
                    and “the scowling anxiety of the soul”;
                    “creator”, not “of favor”, but
                    “all-popular favor”; and “dispenser of the
                    pleasure of the hearers”; “he hid,” not
                    “with branches,” but “with the branches of the
                    forest”; “he covered,” not “his
                    body,” but “the nakedness of his body.” He also
                    calls desire “counter-initiative of the soul”—an
                    expression which is at once compound and an epithet, so that it becomes
                    poetry—and “the excess of his depravity so beyond all
                    bounds.” Hence those who employ poetic language by their lack of taste
                    make the style ridiculous and frigid, and such idle chatter produces obscurity;
                    for when words are piled upon one who already knows, it destroys perspicuity by
                    a cloud of verbiage. People use compound words, when a thing has no name and the
                    word is easy to combine, as <foreign lang="greek">χρονοτριβεῖν</foreign>, to
                    pass time; but if the practice is abused, the style becomes entirely poetical.
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1406b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>This is why compound words
                    are especially employed by dithyrambic poets, who are full of noise; strange
                    words by epic poets, for they imply dignity and self-assertion; metaphor to
                    writers of iambics, who now employ them, as we have stated.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="4"/>The fourth cause of frigidity of style is to be
                    found in metaphors; for metaphors also are inappropriate, some because they are
                    ridiculous—for the comic poets also employ them—others
                    because they are too dignified and somewhat tragic; and if they are farfetched,
                    they are obscure, as when Gorgias says: “Affairs pale and
                    bloodless”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">On this passage
                        Thompson
                        (<title>Gorgias</title>, p. 179) says: “The
                        metaphor of reaping and sowing is a mere commonplace . . . but
                        ‘pallid and bloodless affairs’ is a phrase which would
                        need apology even from a modern.” On the other hand, it is
                        difficult to see what objection there is to calling the
                        <title>Odyssey</title>
                        “a beautiful mirror of human
                        life.” Another reading is <foreign lang="greek">ἔναιμα</foreign>, which Cope translates “events
                        fresh with the
                        blood in them.” If the two extracts are taken together, it is
                        suggested (apparently by the editor of Cope's notes) that
                        the sense may be: “things green and unripe (flushed with
                        sap), and this was the crop which you . . .,” the
                        adjectives referring to green and unripe stalks of corn.
                    </note>
                    ;
                    “you have sown shame and reaped misfortune”; for this is too
                    much like poetry. And as Alcidamas calls philosophy “a bulwark of the
                    laws,”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Or, “a barrier
                        against the laws.” This is the general meaning of <foreign lang="greek">ἐπιτείχισμα</foreign>, a
                        border fortress commanding an
                        enemy's country.
                    </note>
                    and the <title>Odyssey</title> “a
                    beautiful mirror of human life,” and “introducing no such
                    plaything in poetry.” All these expressions fail to produce
                    persuasion, for the reasons stated. As for what Gorgias said to the swallow
                    which, flying over his head, let fall her droppings upon him, it was in the best
                    tragic style. He exclaimed, “Fie, for shame, Philomela!”;
                    for there would have been nothing in this act disgraceful for a bird, whereas it
                    would have been for a young lady. The reproach therefore was appropriate,
                    addressing her as she was, not as she is.
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="4"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>The simile also
                    is a metaphor; for there is very little difference. When the poet says of
                    Achilles,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Compare
                        <bibl n="Hom. Il. 22.164" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il. 22.164</bibl>
                        <foreign lang="greek">ἐνάντιον ὦρτο λεὼν ὥς</foreign>.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>he rushed on like a lion,</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    it is a simile; if he says, “a lion, he rushed on,”
                    it is a metaphor; for because both are courageous, he transfers the sense and
                    calls Achilles a lion.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>The simile is also
                    useful in prose, but should be less frequently used, for there is something
                    poetical about it. Similes must be used like metaphors, which only differ in the
                    manner stated.<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>The following are examples of
                    similes. Androtion<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Pupil of Isocrates and
                    historical writer. Idrieus was a prince of Caria, who had been
                    imprisoned.
                </note> said of Idrieus that he was like curs just unchained; for as
                    they attack and bite, so he when loosed from his bonds was dangerous. Again,
                    Theodamas likened Archidamus to a Euxenus ignorant of geometry, by
                    proportion;<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Meaning that there was no
                    difference between Euxenus without a knowledge of geometry and Archidamus
                    with a knowledge of geometry. The proportion of geometrical knowledge will
                    remain the same, so that Archidamus can be called an ungeometrical Euxenus,
                    and Euxenus a geometrical Archidamus (see 4.4, note for
                    “by proportion”).
                </note> for Euxenus
                    “will be Archidamus acquainted with geometry.” Again, Plato
                    in the
                    <title>Republic</title>
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Plat. Rep. 469d" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Plat. Rep. 469d</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    compares those who
                    strip the dead to curs, which bite stones, but do not touch those who throw
                    them; he also says that the people is like a ship's captain who is vigorous, but
                    rather deaf;
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Plat. Rep. 488a" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Plat.
                        Rep. 488a</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    that poets' verses resemble those who are in
                    the bloom of youth but lack beauty;
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Plat. Rep. 601b" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Plat. Rep. 601b</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    for neither the one
                    after they have lost their bloom, nor the others after they have been broken
                    up,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">If metrical restrictions have been
                        removed and they are read as prose.
                    </note>
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1407a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>appear the same as before.
                    Pericles said that the Samians were like children who cry while they accept the
                    scraps.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Meaning that they did not
                        appreciate the benefits received from the Athenians, who conquered the
                        islands (<date value="-440" authname="-440">440</date> B.C.).
                    </note>
                    He
                    also compared the Boeotians to holm-oaks; for just as these are beaten down by
                    knocking against each other,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Or,
                    “are cut down by axes, the handles of which are made of their own
                    wood.”
                </note> so are the Boeotians by their civil strife.
                    Demosthenes compared the people to passengers who are seasick.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes"
                                                                                        place="unspecified">It is
                    disputed whether Demosthenes is the
                    orator or the Athenian general in the Peloponnesian War. The point of the
                    comparison is that in a democracy the general instability of political
                    conditions makes the people sick of the existing state of things and eager
                    for a change.
                </note> Democrates said that orators resembled nurses who gulp
                    down the morsel and rub the babies' lips with the spittle.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Aristoph. Kn. 715" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Aristoph. Kn.
                        715-718</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    Antisthenes likened the skinny Cephisodotus to incense,
                    for he also gives pleasure by wasting away. All such expressions may be used as
                    similes or metaphors, so that all that are approved as metaphors will obviously
                    also serve as similes which are metaphors without the details.<milestone unit="section" n="4"/>But
                    in all cases the metaphor from proportion should
                    be reciprocal and applicable to either of the two things of the same genus; for
                    instance, if the goblet is the shield of Dionysus, then the shield may properly
                    be called the goblet of Ares.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">As the shield is
                        to Ares, so is the goblet to Dionysus. Proportion is defined (<bibl n="Aristot. Nic. Eth. 1131a"
                                                                                            default="NO" valid="yes">
                            Aristot. Nic. Eth. 5.3.8</bibl>)
                        as “an equality of ratios, implying four terms at the
                        least,” and the proportional metaphor is one in which the second
                        term is to the first as the fourth is to the third; for then one can by
                        metaphor substitute the fourth for the second, or the second for the fourth.
                        Let A be Dionysus, B a goblet, C Ares, D a shield. Then by the definition,
                        the goblet is to Dionysus as the shield is to Ares. The metaphor consists in
                        transferring to the goblet the name belonging to its analogue the shield.
                        Sometimes an addition is made by way of explanation of the word in its new
                        sense, and the goblet may be described as the shield of Dionysus and the
                        shield as the goblet of Ares. The shield and the goblet both come under the
                        same genus, being characteristics of a deity, and can therefore be
                        reciprocally transferred (<bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1457b" default="NO" valid="yes">Aristot.
                            Poet. 21.4</bibl>).
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="5"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>Such then are
                    the elements of speech. But purity,<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>which is the
                    foundation of style, depends upon five rules.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>First, connecting
                    particles should be introduced in their natural order,
                    before or after, as they require; thus, <foreign lang="greek">μέν</foreign> and
                    <foreign lang="greek">ἐγὼ μέν</foreign>
                    require to be followed by
                    <foreign lang="greek">δέ</foreign>
                    and <foreign lang="greek">ὁ
                    δέ</foreign>. Further, they should be made to correspond whilst the hearer
                    still recollects; they should not be put too far apart, nor should a clause be
                    introduced before the necessary connection
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The
                        apodosis. <foreign lang="greek">ἀποδιδόναι</foreign> is used in the sense
                        of introducing a clause answering to the <foreign lang="greek">πρότασις</foreign>, and <foreign
                                lang="greek">ἀπόδοσις
                        </foreign> for
                        this answering clause.
                    </note>
                    ; for this is rarely appropriate. For instance,
                    “As for me, I, after he had told me—for Cleon came begging
                    and praying—set out, taking them with me.” For in this
                    phrase several connecting words have been foisted in before the one which is to
                    furnish the apodosis; and if the interval between “I” and
                    “set out” is too great, the result is obscurity.<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>The first rule
                    therefore is to make a proper use of
                    connecting particles; the second, to employ special, not generic terms.
                    <milestone unit="section" n="4"/>The third consists in avoiding ambiguous
                    terms, unless you deliberately intend the opposite, like those who, having
                    nothing to say, yet pretend to say something; such people accomplish this by the
                    use of verse, after the manner of Empedocles.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Of <placeName key="tgn,7003808"
                                                                                         authname="tgn,7003808">
                        Agrigentum
                    </placeName> (c.
                        490-430), poet, philosopher, and physician. Among other legends
                        connected with him, he is said to have thrown himself into the crater of
                        <placeName key="tgn,7003867" authname="tgn,7003867">Etna</placeName>, so that by suddenly
                        disappearing he might be thought to be a god. His chief work was a poem
                        called Nature, praised by Lucretius. The principles of things are the four
                        elements, fire, air, water, and earth, which are unalterable and
                        indestructible. Love and hate, alternately prevailing, regulate the periods
                        of the formation of the world. The existing fragments corroborate
                        Aristotle's statement.
                    </note>
                    For the long circumlocution takes in the
                    hearers, who find themselves affected like the majority of those who listen to
                    the soothsayers. For when the latter utter their ambiguities, they also assent;
                    for example,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Croesus, by crossing the Halys, shall ruin a mighty dominion.
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hdt. 1.53" default="NO"
                                                                                             valid="yes">Hdt.
                                    1.53</bibl>, <bibl n="Hdt. 1.91" default="NO" valid="yes">Hdt. 1.91</bibl>. Croesus
                                    consulted the Delphian oracle whether he should attack Cyrus the
                                    Persian or not. Encouraged by the ambiguous oracle, he did so,
                                    but was utterly defeated.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1407b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>And as there is less chance of
                    making a mistake when speaking generally, diviners express themselves in general
                    terms on the question of fact; for, in playing odd or even, one is more likely
                    to be right if he says “even” or “odd”
                    than if he gives a definite number, and similarly one who says “it
                    will be” than if he states “when.” This is why
                    soothsayers do not further define the exact time. All such ambiguities are
                    alike, wherefore they should be avoided, except for some such reason.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The deliberate intention to mislead.</note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="5"/>The fourth rule consists in keeping the genders
                    distinct—masculine, feminine, and neuter,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><foreign lang="greek">σκεύη</foreign>,
                        “inanimate
                        things,” the classification probably being male, female, and
                        inanimate, not the grammatical one of masculine, feminine, and
                        neuter.
                    </note>
                    as laid down by Protagoras; these also must be properly
                    introduced:<milestone unit="section" n="6"/>“She, having come
                    (<emph>fem</emph>.) and having conversed
                    (<emph>fem</emph>.) with me, went away.” The
                    fifth rule consists in observing number, according as many, few, or one are
                    referred to: “They, having come (<emph>pl</emph>.),
                    began to beat (<emph>pl</emph>.) me.”
                </p>
                <p>Generally speaking, that which is written should be easy to read or easy to
                    utter, which is the same thing. Now, this is not the case when there is a number
                    of connecting particles, or when the punctuation is hard, as in the writings of
                    Heraclitus.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Heraclitus of <placeName key="tgn,7002499"
                                                                                                    authname="tgn,7002499">
                        Ephesus
                    </placeName> (c. 535-475).
                        His chief work was on Nature. From the harshness of his language and the
                        carelessness of his style he was called <foreign lang="greek">ὁ
                            σκοτεινός
                        </foreign> (the obscure). According to him, fire
                        was the origin of all things; all things become fire, and then fire becomes
                        all other things. All things are in a constant state of flux; all is the
                        same and yet not the same. Knowledge is founded upon sensual perception, but
                        only the gods possess knowledge in perfection.
                    </note>
                    For it is hard, since
                    it is uncertain to which word another belongs, whether to that which follows or
                    that which precedes; for instance, at the beginning of his composition he says:
                    “Of this reason which exists<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Or,
                        “although this reason exists for ever men are born . . . without
                        understanding” (Welldon).
                    </note> always men are
                    ignorant,” where it is uncertain whether “always”
                    should go with “which exists” or with “are
                    ignorant.”<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>Further, a solecism
                    results from not appropriately connecting or joining two words with a word which
                    is equally suitable to both.<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>For instance, in speaking of
                    “sound” and “color”, the word
                    “seeing” should not be used, for it is not suitable to both,
                    whereas “perceiving” is. It also causes obscurity, if you do
                    not say at the outset what you mean, when you intend to insert a number of
                    details in the middle; for instance, if you say: “I intended after
                    having spoken to him thus and thus and in this way to set out” instead
                    of “I intended to set out after having spoken to him,” and
                    then this or that happened, in this or that manner.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="6"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>The following
                    rules contribute to loftiness of style. Use of the description instead of the
                    name of a thing; for instance, do not say “circle,” but
                    “a plane figure, all the points of which are equidistant from the
                    center.” But for the purpose of conciseness the reverse—use
                    the name instead of the description.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>You should
                    do the same to express anything foul or indecent; if the foulness is in the
                    description, use the name; if in the name, the description.<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>Use
                    metaphors and epithets by way of illustration,
                    taking care, however, to avoid what is too poetical.<milestone unit="section" n="4"/>Use the plural
                    for the singular, after the manner of the poets, who,
                    although there is only one harbor, say
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="lyric" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>to Achaean harbors,</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    and,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="lyric" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Here are the many-leaved folds of the tablet.
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Eur. IT 727"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Eur. IT
                                    727</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="5"/>You should avoid linking up, but each word
                    should have its own article: <foreign lang="greek">τῆς γυναικὸς τῆς
                    ἡμετέρας</foreign>. But for conciseness, the reverse: <foreign lang="greek">τῆς ἡμετέρας
                    γυναικός</foreign>.<milestone unit="section" n="6"/>Employ a connecting particle or for conciseness
                    omit it, but avoid
                    destroying the connection;
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1408a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>for
                    instance “having gone and having conversed with him,” or,
                    “having gone, I conversed with him.”<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>Also the practice of Antimachus
                    is useful, that of
                    describing a thing by the qualities it does not possess; thus, in speaking of
                    the hill Teumessus,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">In <placeName key="tgn,7002683"
                                                                                         authname="tgn,7002683">
                        Boeotia</placeName>. The quotation is from the
                        <title>
                            <placeName key="tgn,4011135" authname="tgn,4011135">Thebaid</placeName>
                        </title>
                        of Antimachus of Claros (c.
                        <date value="-450" authname="-450">450</date>
                        B.C.). The Alexandrians placed him next to Homer among the epic
                        poets. In his eulogy of the little hill, he went on to attribute to it all
                        the good qualities it did <emph>not</emph> possess, a process which could
                        obviously be carried on
                        <emph>ad infinitum.</emph>
                    </note>
                    he says,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>There is a little windswept hill;</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    for in this way amplification may be carried on <emph>ad
                    infinitum.
                </emph> This method may be applied to things good and bad, in
                    whichever way it may be useful. Poets also make use of this in inventing words,
                    as a melody “without strings” or “without the
                    lyre”; for they employ epithets from negations, a course which is
                    approved in proportional metaphors, as for instance, to say that the sound of
                    the trumpet is a melody without the lyre.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="7"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>Propriety of
                    style will be obtained by the expression of emotion and character, and by
                    proportion to the subject matter.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>Style is
                    proportionate to the subject matter when neither weighty matters are treated
                    offhand, nor trifling matters with dignity, and no embellishment is attached to
                    an ordinary word; otherwise there is an appearance of comedy, as in the poetry
                    of Cleophon,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">By some identified with the
                        tragic poet spoken of in <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1448a" default="NO" valid="yes">Aristot. Poet.
                            2</bibl>.
                        His manner of expression, due to the wish to use fine language, was
                        ridiculous owing to its being out of harmony with the subject. Others
                        consider that he was not a poet at all but an orator. <foreign lang="greek">πότνια</foreign> was
                        a title of respect, applied to females, whether
                        they were goddesses or ordinary women.
                    </note>
                    who used certain expressions
                    that reminded one of saying “madam fig.”<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>Style expresses emotion,
                    when a man speaks with anger
                    of wanton outrage; with indignation and reserve, even in mentioning them, of
                    things foul or impious; with admiration of things praiseworthy; with lowliness
                    of things pitiable; and so in all other cases.<milestone unit="section" n="4"/>Appropriate style<lb
                        ed="Bekker" n="20"/>also makes the fact appear credible;
                    for the mind of the hearer is imposed upon<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Or,
                    “draws a wrong conclusion.”
                </note> under the impression
                    that the speaker is speaking the truth, because, in such circumstances, his
                    feelings are the same, so that he thinks (even if it is not the case as
                    the speaker puts it) that things are as he represents them; and the
                    hearer always sympathizes with one who speaks emotionally, even though he really
                    says nothing.<milestone unit="section" n="5"/>This is why speakers often
                    confound their hearers by mere noise.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="6"/>Character also may be expressed by the proof
                    from signs, because to each class and habit there is an appropriate style. I
                    mean class in reference to age—child, man, or old man; to
                    sex—man or woman; to country—Lacedaemonian or Thessalian. I
                    call habits those moral states which form a man's character in life;<milestone unit="section"
                                                                                                   n="7"/>for not all
                    habits do this. If then anyone uses the
                    language appropriate to each habit, he will represent the character; for the
                    uneducated man will not say the same things in the same way as the educated. But
                    the hearers also are impressed in a certain way by a device employed <emph>ad
                        nauseam
                    </emph> by writers of speeches:<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Alluding to
                        Isocrates.
                    </note> “Who does not know?”
                    “Everybody knows”; for the hearer agrees, because he is
                    ashamed to appear not to share what is a matter of common knowledge.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="8"/>The opportune or inopportune use of these
                    devices
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1408b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>applies to all kinds
                    of Rhetoric.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Or, “to all the special
                        rules given above.”
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="9"/>But whenever one has gone too far, the remedy
                    may be found in the common piece of advice—that he should rebuke
                    himself in advance;
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The exaggeration should be
                        brought forward first, by way of forestalling the objection, and accompanied
                        by some limiting phrase. Quintilian (<bibl n="Quint. Inst. Orat. 8.3.37" default="NO">Quint.
                            Inst. Orat. 8.3.37</bibl>)
                        gives as examples: “so to say,” “if I may be
                        allowed to say so.”
                    </note>
                    then the excess seems true, since the
                    orator is obviously aware of what he is doing.<milestone unit="section" n="10"/>Further, one ought
                    not to make use of all kinds of correspondence<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes"
                                                                        place="unspecified">Adaptation of voice,
                        features, etc., to the
                        subject.
                    </note> together; for in this manner the hearer is deceived. I mean,
                    for instance, if the language is harsh, the voice, features, and all things
                    connected should not be equally harsh; otherwise what each really is becomes
                    evident. But if you do this in one instance and not in another, the art escapes
                    notice, although the result is the same. If mild sentiments are harshly
                    expressed or harsh sentiments mildly, the speech lacks persuasiveness.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="11"/>Compound words, a number of epithets, and
                    “foreign” words especially, are appropriate to an emotional
                    speaker; for when a man is enraged it is excusable for him to call an evil
                    “high-as-heaven” or “stupendous.” He may
                    do the same when he has gripped his audience and filled it with enthusiasm,
                    either by praise, blame, anger, or friendliness, as Isocrates does at the end of
                    his
                    <title>Panegyricus</title>
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Isoc. 4.186" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Isoc. 4.186</bibl>, where <foreign
                            lang="greek">μνήμη
                    </foreign> is the reading, translated “name”
                        above (lit. memory) for the sake of the jingle, which also
                        appears in the Greek of Isocrates. All the Mss. of Aristotle give <foreign lang="greek">γνώμην
                        </foreign> here, which shows that it is a
                        misquotation.
                    </note>
                    : “Oh, the fame and the name!” and
                    “In that they endured.” For such is the language of
                    enthusiastic orators, and it is clear that the hearers accept what they say in a
                    sympathetic spirit. Wherefore this style is appropriate to poetry; for there is
                    something inspired in poetry. It should therefore be used either in this way
                    or<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>when speaking ironically, after the manner of
                    Gorgias, or of Plato in the
                    <title>Phaedrus.</title>
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Plat. Phaedrus 238d" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Plat. Phaedrus 238d</bibl>,
                        <bibl n="Plat. Phaedrus 241e" default="NO" valid="yes">Plat. Phaedrus 241e</bibl>. In the first
                        of these passages
                        <persName>
                            <surname full="yes">Socrates</surname>
                        </persName>
                        attributes his unusual flow of words to the
                        inspiration of the nymphs, and tells Phaedrus not to wonder if he seems to
                        be in a divine fury, for he is not far from breaking out into dithyrambs. An
                        example of the irony (a term implying a certain amount of contempt
                        (2.2.25)) of Gorgias is given in <bibl n="Aristot. Pol. 3.1274b" default="NO" valid="yes">
                            Aristot. Pol. 3.1</bibl>. When asked how a person
                        comes to be a citizen, he answers: “as those are mortars which
                        have been made by mortar-makers, so those are Larissaeans who have been made
                        by artisans ( <foreign lang="greek">δημιουργούς</foreign>); for some of these were
                        <persName>
                            <surname full="yes">Larissa</surname>
                        </persName>
                        -makers ( <foreign lang="greek">λαρισοποιούς</foreign>).” There is a
                        play on the double meaning of <foreign lang="greek">δημιουργός</foreign>,
                        (1) artisan, (2) magistrate,
                        <emph>lit.</emph>
                        people-maker. Larissa-makers means makers of Larissaeans
                        in such numbers that they might be regarded as makers of Larissa itself. It
                        has also been suggested that
                        <foreign lang="greek">λαρισοποιούς</foreign>
                        may mean “kettle-makers,” from <foreign lang="greek">λάρισα</foreign> “a kettle,” so called from
                        having
                        been first made at Larissa, but this seems unnecessary. The point is that
                        Gorgias maintained that all were citizens who were made so by the
                        magistrates, that citizenship was a manufactured article (see W. L.
                        Newman's note on the passage, and W. H. Thompson's Appendix to his edition
                        of Plato's <title>Gorgias</title>).
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="8"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>The form of
                    diction should be neither metrical nor without rhythm. If it is metrical, it
                    lacks persuasiveness, for it appears artificial, and at the same time it
                    distracts the hearer's attention, since it sets him on the watch for the
                    recurrence of such and such a cadence; just as, when the public criers ask,
                    “Whom does the emancipated<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">He did
                    not generally possess full rights of citizenship. The point of the
                    illustration is that the hearer looks for the cadence just as confidently
                    as, when a freedman is asked what patron he selects, every one expects him
                    to say “Cleon.”
                </note> choose for his patron?”
                    the children shout “Cleon.”<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>If it is without rhythm, it is
                    unlimited, whereas it ought to be limited
                    (but not by meter); for that which is unlimited is unpleasant
                    and unknowable. Now all things are limited by number, and the number belonging
                    to the form of diction is rhythm, of which the meters are divisions.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Bywater's emendation for <foreign
                            lang="greek">τμητά
                    </foreign> of the Mss. Aristotle seems to be referring to the
                        Pythagorean theory that “number” is the regulating force
                        in all things, and in giving shape to language “number”
                        is rhythm, which reduces a formless mass of words to order.
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>Wherefore prose must be rhythmical, but not
                    metrical, otherwise it will be a poem. Nor must this rhythm be rigorously
                    carried out, but only up to a certain point.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="4"/>Of the different rhythms the heroic is
                    dignified, but lacking the harmony of ordinary conversation; the iambic is the
                    language of the many, wherefore of all meters it is most used in common speech;
                    but speech should be dignified and calculated to rouse the hearer. The trochaic
                    is too much like the cordax; this is clear from the tetrameters,
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1409a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>which form a tripping rhythm. There
                    remains the paean, used by rhetoricians from the time of Thrasymachus, although
                    they could not define it.
                </p>
                <p>The paean is a third kind of rhythm closely related to those already mentioned;
                    for its proportion is 3 to 2, that of the others 1 to 1 and 2 to 1, with both of
                    which the paean, whose proportion is 1 1/2 to 1, is connected.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The heroic rhythm (dactyls, spondees,
                        and anapests) is as 1 to 1, two short syllables being equal to one
                        long; trochaic and iambic 2 to 1 on the same principle; paean, 3 to 2
                        (three shorts and one long), being the mean between the
                        other two.
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="5"/>All the other meters then are to be disregarded
                    for the reasons stated, and also because they are metrical; but the paean should
                    be retained, because it is the only one of the rhythms mentioned which is not
                    adapted to a metrical system, so that it is most likely to be undetected.
                    <milestone unit="section" n="6"/>At the present day one kind of paean alone
                    is employed, at the beginning as well as at the end;
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Understanding <foreign lang="greek">καὶ
                        τελευτῶντες</foreign>.
                    </note>
                    the end, however, ought to differ from the
                    beginning. Now there are two kinds of paeans, opposed to each other. The one is
                    appropriate at the beginning, where in fact it is used. It begins with a long
                    syllable and ends with three short:
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="lyric" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l><foreign lang="greek">Δα¯λο˘γε˘νε˘ς εἴτε
                                Λυ˘κι˘αν</foreign>, (“O
                                Delos-born, or it may be <placeName key="tgn,7001294" authname="tgn,7001294">
                                    Lycia</placeName>”),
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    and
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="lyric" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>
                                <foreign lang="greek">Χρυ¯σε˘ο˘κό˘μα¯
                                    Ἕ˘κα˘τε˘ παῖ
                                    Διό˘ς
                                </foreign>
                                (“Golden-haired
                                far-darter, son of Zeus”).
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    The other on the contrary begins with three short syllables and ends
                    with one long one:
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="lyric" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>
                                <foreign lang="greek">με˘τὰ˘ δε˘ γᾶν
                                    ὕ˘δα˘τά˘ τ᾽
                                    ὠκε˘α˘νὸν
                                    ἠφά˘νι˘σε˘νύξ
                                </foreign>
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">All three attributed to Simonides
                                    (Frag. 26 B: <title>P.L.G.</title>).
                                </note>
                                (“after earth and waters, night obscured
                                ocean”).
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    This is a suitable ending, for the short syllable, being incomplete,
                    mutilates the cadence. But the period should be broken off by a long syllable
                    and<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>the end should be clearly marked, not by the
                    scribe nor by a punctuation mark,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">A dash below
                        the first word of a line, indicating the end of a sentence.
                    </note> but by
                    the rhythm itself.<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>That the style should be
                    rhythmical and not unrhythmical, and what rhythms and what arrangement of them
                    make it of this character, has now been sufficiently shown.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="9"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>The style must
                    be either continuous and united by connecting particles, like the dithyrambic
                    preludes, or periodic, like the antistrophes of the ancient poets. The
                    continuous style is the ancient one; for example,<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>“This is the
                    exposition of the investigation of Herodotus
                    of <placeName key="perseus,Thurii" authname="perseus,Thurii">Thurii</placeName>.” It was
                    formerly used by all, but now is used only by a few. By a continuous style I
                    mean that which has no end in itself and only stops when the sense is complete.
                    It is unpleasant, because it is endless, for all wish to have the end in sight.
                    That explains why runners, just when they have reached the goal,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><foreign lang="greek">καμπτῆρες</foreign>,
                        properly the turning-point of the
                        <foreign lang="greek">δίαυλος</foreign>
                        or double course, is here used for the goal itself.
                    </note>
                    lose their breath
                    and strength, whereas before, when the end is in sight, they show no signs of
                    fatigue.<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>Such is the continuous style. The
                    other style consists of periods, and by period I mean a sentence that has a
                    beginning and end in itself and a magnitude that can be easily grasped.
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1409b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>What is written in this style
                    is pleasant and easy to learn, pleasant because it is the opposite of that which
                    is unlimited, because the hearer at every moment thinks he is securing something
                    for himself and that some conclusion has been reached; whereas it is unpleasant
                    neither to foresee nor to get to the end of anything. It is easy to learn,
                    because it can be easily retained in the memory. The reason is that the periodic
                    style has number, which of all things is the easiest to remember; that explains
                    why all learn verse with greater facility than prose,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><foreign lang="greek">τῶν χύδην</foreign>:
                        lit. what is
                        poured fourth promiscuously: in flowing, unfettered language
                        (Liddell and
                        <persName>
                            <surname full="yes">Scott</surname>
                        </persName>
                        ).
                    </note>
                    for it has number by which it can be
                    measured.<milestone unit="section" n="4"/>But the period must be completed with
                    the sense and not stop short, as in the iambics of Sophocles,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Really from the <title>Meleager</title> of
                        Euripides, Frag.
                        515 (<title>T.G.F.</title>). The break in the sense comes
                        after <foreign lang="greek">γαῖα, Πελοπίας χθονός</foreign> really
                        belonging to the next line: <foreign lang="greek">ἐν ἀντιπόρθμοις πέδι᾽
                            ἔχουσ᾽ εὐδαίμονα</foreign>. As it stands in the text, the line
                        implies that Calydon was in <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">
                            Peloponnesus</placeName>, which of course it was not. The meaning then is:
                        “This is the land of Calydon, with its fertile plains in the
                        country over against <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">
                            Peloponnesus</placeName>” (on the opposite side of the
                        strait, near the mouth of the Corinthian gulf).
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>This is Calydon, territory of the land of Pelops;</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    for by a division of this kind it is possible to suppose the contrary
                    of the fact, as in the example, that Calydon is in <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
                                                                                  authname="tgn,7017076">
                    Peloponnesus</placeName>.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="5"/>A period may be composed of clauses, or simple.
                    The former is a complete sentence, distinct in its parts and easy to repeat in a
                    breath, not divided like the period in the line of Sophocles above, but when it
                    is taken as a whole.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">It does not consist in
                        simply dividing off any words from the context as the speaker pleases, but
                        the parts of the sentence as a whole are properly constructed and
                        distinguished and the sense also is complete.
                    </note> By clause I mean one of
                    the two parts of this period, and by a simple period one that consists of only
                    one clause.<milestone unit="section" n="6"/>But neither clauses nor periods
                    should be curtailed or too long. If too short, they often make the hearer
                    stumble; for when he is hurrying on<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>towards the measure
                    of which he already has a definite idea, if he is checked by the speaker
                    stopping, a sort of stumble is bound to occur in consequence of the sudden stop.
                    If too long, they leave the hearer behind, as those who do not turn till past
                    the ordinary limit leave behind those who are walking with them. Similarly long
                    periods assume the proportions of a speech and resemble dithyrambic preludes.
                    This gives rise to what Democritus of
                    <placeName key="tgn,7002670" authname="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName>
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">A well-known
                        musician.
                    </note>
                    jokingly rebuked in Melanippides,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Of <placeName key="tgn,7010922"
                                                                                         authname="tgn,7010922">
                        Melos</placeName>. He wrote
                        rambling dithyrambic <emph>preludes</emph> without strophic correspondence.
                        Others take <foreign lang="greek">ἀναβολή</foreign> to mean an entire
                        <emph>ode</emph>.
                    </note>
                    who instead of antistrophes composed
                    dithyrambic preludes:
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>A man does harm to himself in doing harm to another, and a long
                                prelude is most deadly to one who composes it;
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hes. WD 265"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hes. WD 265</bibl>. The
                                    second line is a parody of 266,
                                    <foreign lang="greek">ἡ δὲ
                                        κακὴ βουλὴ τῷ βουλεύσαντι
                                        κακίστη.
                                    </foreign>
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    for these verses may be applied to those who employ long clauses.
                    Again, if the clauses are too short, they do not make a period, so that the
                    hearer himself is carried away headlong.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="7"/>The clauses of the periodic style are divided or
                    opposed; divided, as in the following sentence: “I have often wondered
                    at those who gathered together the general assemblies and instituted the
                    gymnastic contests”;
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The beginning
                        of <bibl n="Isoc. 4" default="NO" valid="yes">Isoc. 4</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    opposed, in which, in each of
                    the two clauses, one contrary is brought close to another, or the same word is
                    coupled with both contraries;
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1410a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>for instance, “They were useful to both, both those who stayed and
                    those who followed; for the latter they gained in addition greater possessions
                    than they had at home, for the former they left what was sufficient in their own
                    country.” Here “staying behind,”
                    “following,” “sufficient,”
                    “more” are contraries. Again: “to those who need
                    money and those who wish to enjoy it”; where
                    “enjoying” is contrary to “acquiring.”
                    Again: “It often happens in these vicissitudes that the wise are
                    unsuccessful, while fools succeed”: “At once they were
                    deemed worthy of the prize of valor and not long after won the command of the
                    sea”: “To sail over the mainland, to go by land over the
                    sea, bridging over the <placeName key="tgn,7002638" authname="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName> and
                    digging through <placeName key="tgn,7002722" authname="tgn,7002722">Athos</placeName>”:
                    “And that, though citizens by nature, they were deprived of the rights
                    of citizenship by law”: “For some of them perished
                    miserably, others saved themselves disgracefully”:
                    “Privately to employ barbarians as servants,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                        “To dwell with us”
                        (Jebb). The point seems to be that the barbarian domestics
                        were in a comfortable position as compared with those of the allies who were
                        reduced to slavery; and there is a contrast between the desire of getting
                        servants for private convenience, while in a matter affecting public life
                        indifference was shown.
                    </note> but publicly to view with indifference many
                    of the allies reduced to slavery”: “Either to possess it
                    while living or to leave it behind when dead.”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">All the above quotations are from <bibl
                            n="Isoc. 4.1" default="NO" valid="yes">Isoc. 4.1, 35, 41,
                        48, 72, 89, 105, 149, 181, 186</bibl>, with slight variations. The last
                        quotation is part of the sentence of which the beginning appears in 7.11
                        above. The whole runs: “And how great must we consider the fame
                        and the name and the glory which those who have highly distinguished
                        themselves in such deeds of valor will either have when living or will leave
                        behind after their death.”
                    </note>
                    And what some one said against
                    Pitholaus and Lycophron
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">They murdered
                        Alexander, tyrant of Pherae, being instigated by their sister, his wife.
                        Nothing is known of the case referred to. According to Cope, the meaning is:
                        “When they were at Pherae, they used to sell you as slaves, but
                        now they have come to buy you” (referring to bribery in
                        court). Others take <foreign lang="greek">ὠνεῖσθαι</foreign> in a
                        passive sense: “they have been bought,” i.e. have had to
                        sell themselves to you.
                    </note>
                    in the lawcourt: “These men, who
                    used to sell you when they were at home, having come to you have bought
                    you.”<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>All these passages are examples of
                    antithesis.<milestone unit="section" n="8"/>This kind of style is pleasing,
                    because contraries are easily understood and even more so when placed side by
                    side, and also because antithesis resembles a syllogism; for refutation is a
                    bringing together of contraries.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="9"/>Such then is the nature of antithesis; equality
                    of clauses is parisosis; the similarity of the final syllables of each clause
                    paromoiosis. This must take place at the beginning or end of the clauses. At the
                    beginning the similarity is always shown in entire words; at the end, in the
                    last syllables, or the inflections of one and the same word, or the repetition
                    of the same word. For instance, at the beginning: <foreign lang="greek">Ἀγρὸν
                        γὰρ ἔλαβεν ἀργὸν παρ᾽ αὐτοῦ</foreign>,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                        <bibl n="Aristoph. Fr. 649" default="NO">Aristoph. frag. 649</bibl>
                        (
                        <persName>
                            <surname full="yes">Kock</surname>
                        </persName>
                        , <title>Com.
                        Att. Frag.
                    </title> 1.<date value="1880" authname="1880">1880</date>).
                    </note>
                    “for he received from him land untilled”;
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l><foreign lang="greek">δωρητοί τ᾽ ἐπέλοντο παράρρητοί τ᾽
                                ἐπέεσσιν</foreign>,
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 9.526"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Il. 9.526</bibl>.
                                </note>
                                “they were ready to accept gifts and to be persuaded by
                                words;”
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    at the end: <foreign lang="greek">ᾠήθησαν αὐτὸν παιδίον
                        τετοκέναι, ἀλλ᾽ αὐτοῦ αἴτιον γεγονέναι</foreign>,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes"
                                                                               place="unspecified">The text is obviously
                        corrupt.
                    </note> “they thought
                    that he was the father of a child, but that he was the cause of it”;
                    <foreign lang="greek">ἐν πλείσταις δὲ φροντίσι καὶ ἐν ἐλαχίσταις
                        ἐλπίσιν</foreign>, “in the greatest anxiety and the smallest
                    hopes.” Inflections of the same word: <foreign lang="greek">ἄξιος
                        δὲ σταθῆναι χαλκοῦς, οὐκ ἄξιος ὢν χαλκοῦ</foreign>,
                    “worthy of a bronze statue, not being worth a brass
                    farthing.” Repetition of a word: <foreign lang="greek">σὺ δ᾽ αὐτὸν
                        καὶ ζῶντα ἔλεγες κακῶς καὶ νῦν γράφεις κακῶς</foreign>,
                    “while he lived you spoke ill of him, now he is dead you write ill of
                    him.” Resemblance of one syllable: <foreign lang="greek">τί ἂν
                        ἔπαθες δεινόν, εἰ ἄνδρ᾽ εἶδες ἀργόν</foreign>, “what ill
                    would you have suffered, if you had seen an idle man?” All these
                    figures may be found in the same sentence at once—
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1410b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>antithesis, equality of clauses, and
                    similarity of endings. In the
                    <title>Theodectea</title>
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">See Introduction.</note>
                    nearly all the beginnings
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Roemer's text has <foreign lang="greek">
                        ἀρεταί
                    </foreign> (excellences).
                    </note>
                    of periods
                    have been enumerated.<milestone unit="section" n="10"/>There are also false
                    antitheses, as in the verse of Epicharmus:
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="troch" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l><foreign lang="greek">τόκα μὲν ἐν τήνων ἐγὼν ἦν, τόκα δὲ
                                παρὰ τήνοις ἐγών</foreign>, “at one time I was in
                                their house, at another I was with them.”
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">There is no real antithesis, the
                                    sense of both clauses being the same.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="10"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>Having settled
                    these questions, we must next state the sources of smart and popular sayings.
                    They are produced either by natural genius or by practice; to show what they are
                    is the function of this inquiry.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>Let us
                    therefore begin by giving a full list of them, and let our starting-point be the
                    following. Easy learning is naturally pleasant to all, and words mean something,
                    so that all words which make us learn something are most pleasant. Now we do not
                    know the meaning of strange words, and proper terms we know already. It is
                    metaphor, therefore, that above all produces this effect; for when Homer
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                        <bibl n="Hom. Od. 24.213" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Od. 24.213</bibl>
                        <foreign lang="greek">ἀλλ᾽ ἔμπης καλάμην γέ σ᾽ ὀΐμαι εἰσορόωντα
                            γιγνώσκειν</foreign>. The words are those of Odysseus, whom Athene had
                        changed into an old beggar, to Eumaeus, his faithful swineherd, in whose
                        house he was staying unrecognized.
                    </note>
                    calls old age stubble, he teaches
                    and informs us through the genus; for both have lost their bloom.<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>
                    The similes of the poets also have the same effect;
                    wherefore, if they are well constructed, an impression of smartness is produced.
                    For the simile, as we have said, is a metaphor differing only by the addition of
                    a word,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><foreign lang="greek">προσθέσει</foreign>:
                        the addition of the particle of comparison <foreign lang="greek">ὡς. προθέσει</foreign> (the
                        reading of the
                        <persName>
                            <surname full="yes">Paris</surname>
                        </persName>
                        ms.) would mean,
                        (1) “manner of setting forth”
                        (Cope), or (2) “a metaphor,
                        with a preface” (Jebb) (but the meaning
                        of this is not clear). The simile only says that one thing
                        <emph>resembles</emph>
                        another, not, like the metaphor, that it
                        <emph>is</emph>
                        another; since the speaker does not say this, the result is
                        that the mind of the hearer does not go into the matter, and so the chance
                        of instruction, of acquiring some information, is lost.
                    </note>
                    wherefore it
                    is less pleasant because it is longer; it does not say that this
                    <emph>is</emph>
                    that, so that<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>the mind does not even examine this.
                    <milestone unit="section" n="4"/>Of necessity, therefore, all style and
                    enthymemes that give us rapid information are smart. This is the reason why
                    superficial enthymemes, meaning those that are obvious to all and need no mental
                    effort, and those which, when stated, are not understood, are not popular, but
                    only those which are understood the moment they are stated, or those of which
                    the meaning, although not clear at first, comes a little later; for from the
                    latter a kind of knowledge results, from the former neither the one nor the
                    other.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The meaning is: the two kinds of
                        enthymemes mentioned last do convey some information, whereas the
                        superficial enthymemes teach nothing, either at once, or a little later,
                        when reflection has made the meaning clear.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="5"/>In regard to the meaning of what is said, then,
                    such enthymemes are popular. As to style, popularity of form is due to
                    antithetical statement; for instance, “accounting the peace that all
                    shared to be a war against their private interests,”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Isoc. 5.73" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Isoc. 5.73</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    where “war” is opposed to “peace”;
                    <milestone unit="section" n="6"/>as to words, they are popular if they
                    contain metaphor, provided it be neither strange, for then it is difficult to
                    take in at a glance, nor superficial, for then it does not impress the hearer;
                    further, if they set things “before the eyes”; for we ought
                    to see what is being done rather than what is going to be done. We ought
                    therefore to aim at three things—metaphor, antithesis, actuality.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="7"/>Of the four kinds of metaphor
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">In
                        <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1457a" default="NO" valid="yes">Aristot. Poet. 21</bibl>
                        metaphor and its four classes are defined: “Metaphor consists in
                        assigning to a thing the name of something else; and this may take place
                        either from genus to species, or from species to genus, or from species to
                        species, or proportionally. An instance of a metaphor from genus to species
                        is ‘here stands my ship,’ for
                        ‘standing’ is a genus, ‘being
                        moored’ a species; from species to genus: ‘Odysseus
                        truly has wrought a myriad good deeds,’ for
                        ‘myriad’ is a specific large number, used for the
                        generic ‘multitude’; from species to species:
                        ‘having drawn off the life with the bronze’ and
                        ‘having cut it with the unyielding bronze,’ where
                        ‘drawn off’ is used in the sense of
                        ‘cut,’ and ‘cut’ in the sense of
                        ‘drawn off,’ both being species of ‘taking
                        away.’” For the proportional metaphor see note on 4.4
                        above.
                    </note>
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1411a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>the most popular are those
                    based on proportion. Thus, Pericles said that the youth that had perished during
                    the war had disappeared from the State as if the year had lost its
                    springtime.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">1.7.34.</note> Leptines,
                    speaking of the Lacedaemonians, said that he would not let the Athenians stand
                    by and see <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> deprived of one of
                    her eyes. When Chares was eager to have his accounts for the Olynthian war
                    examined, Cephisodotus indignantly exclaimed that, now he had the people by the
                    throat, he was trying to get his accounts examined
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign lang="greek">εὔθυνα</foreign>
                        was the technical
                        term for the examination of accounts to which all public officers had to
                        submit when their term of office expired. Cephisodotus and Chares were both
                        Athenian generals. “Having the people by the throat” may
                        refer to the condition of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>
                        financially and his unsatisfactory conduct of the war. But the phrase
                        <foreign lang="greek">εἰς πνῖγμα τὸν δῆμον ἔχοντα</foreign>
                        is
                        objected to by Cope, who reads
                        <foreign lang="greek">ἀγαγόντα</foreign>
                        and translates: “that he drove the people into a fit of choking by
                        his attempts to offer his accounts for scrutiny in this way,” i.e.
                        he tried to force his accounts down their throats, and nearly choked them.
                        Another reading suggested is
                        <foreign lang="greek">ἄγχοντα</foreign>
                        (throttling so as to choke).
                    </note>
                    ; on another occasion
                    also he exhorted the Athenians to set out for <placeName key="tgn,7002677" authname="tgn,7002677">
                        Euboea
                    </placeName> without delay “and provision themselves there,
                    like the decree of Miltiades.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">This may refer
                        to a decree of Miltiades which was so speedily carried out that it became
                        proverbial. The expedition was undertaken to assist <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
                                                                                       authname="tgn,7002677">Euboea
                        </placeName> against <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">
                            Thebes</placeName>.
                    </note>
                    ” After the
                    Athenians had made peace with
                    <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName>
                    and the maritime cities, Iphicrates indignantly declared “that they
                    had deprived themselves of provisions for the war.”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">By making peace, Iphicrates said that the
                        Athenians had
                        deprived themselves of the opportunity of attacking and plundering a weak
                        maritime city, and so securing provisions for the war. The word <foreign lang="greek">ἐφόδια
                        </foreign> properly means provisions for a journey
                        and travelling expenses.
                    </note>
                    Pitholaus called the Paralus<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The Paralus and
                        Salaminia were the two sacred
                        galleys which conveyed state prisoners.
                    </note> “the bludgeon of
                    the people,” and
                    <placeName key="perseus,Sestos" authname="perseus,Sestos">Sestos</placeName>
                    “the corn-chest<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">It commanded the
                        trade of the Euxine.
                    </note> of the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus" authname="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>.”
                    Pericles recommended that <placeName key="tgn,7011087" authname="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>,
                    “the eyesore of the
                    <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus" authname="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>,” should be
                    removed. Moerocles, mentioning a very “respectable” person
                    by name, declared that he was as much a scoundrel as himself; for whereas that
                    honest man played the scoundrel at 33 per cent. he himself was satisfied with 10
                    per cent.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Moerocles was a contemporary of
                        Demosthenes, and an anti-Macedonian in politics. He seems to have been a
                        money-grubber and was once prosecuted for extortion. The degree of the
                        respectability (or rather, the swindling practices) of
                        each is calculated by their respective profits.
                    </note> And the iambic of
                    Anaxandrides,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Poet of the Middle Comedy:
                        Frag. 68 (
                        <persName>
                            <surname full="yes">Kock</surname>
                        </persName>
                        ,
                        <title>Com. Att. Frag.</title>
                        2.). The metaphor in <foreign lang="greek">ὑπερήμενοι</foreign> is from those who failed to keep
                        the
                        term of payment of a fine or debt. Cope translates: “I find
                        ( <foreign lang="greek">μοι</foreign>) the young ladies
                        are . . .”
                    </note>
                    on girls who were<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>slow to
                    marry,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>My daughters are “past the time” of marriage.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    And the saying of Polyeuctus<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Athenian
                        orator, contemporary of Demosthenes
                    </note> upon a certain paralytic named
                    Speusippus, “that he could not keep quiet, although Fortune had bound
                    him in a five-holed pillory of disease.” Cephisodotus called the
                    triremes “parti-colored mills,”<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">As grinding
                        down the tributary states. They differed from
                        ordinary mills in being gaily painted.
                    </note> and
                    [Diogenes] the Cynic used to say that the taverns
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Contrasted with the Spartan
                        “messes,” which were of a plain and simple character, at
                        which all the citizens dined together. The tavern orgies, according to
                        Diogenes, represented these at <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">
                            Athens</placeName>.
                    </note>
                    were “the messes” of
                    <placeName key="tgn,7002681" authname="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>. Aesion<note resp="Freese"
                                                                                                        anchored="yes"
                                                                                                        place="unspecified">
                        Athenian orator, opponent of Demosthenes.
                    </note> used to say
                    that they had “drained” the State into <placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">
                        Sicily</placeName>,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Referring to the
                        disastrous Sicilian expedition.
                    </note> which is a metaphor
                    and sets the thing before the eyes. His words “so that <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                                                                                      authname="tgn,1000074">Greece
                    </placeName> uttered a cry” are also in a
                    manner a metaphor and a vivid one. And again, as Cephisodotus bade the Athenians
                    take care not to hold their “concourses” too often; and in
                    the same way Isocrates, who spoke of those “who rush
                    together” in the assemblies.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Isoc. 5.12" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Isoc. 5.12</bibl>. Both <foreign
                            lang="greek">συνδρομάς
                    </foreign> and
                        <foreign lang="greek">συντρέχοντας</foreign>
                        refer to the collecting of a mob in a state of excitement.
                    </note>
                    And as
                    Lysias says in his Funeral Oration, that it was right that <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                                                                                          authname="tgn,1000074">Greece
                    </placeName> should cut her hair at the tomb of
                    those who fell at <placeName key="tgn,7002340" authname="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>, since her
                    freedom was buried along with their valor. If the speaker had said that it was
                    fitting that <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> should weep, her
                    valor being buried with them, it would have been a metaphor and a vivid one,
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1411b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>whereas
                    “freedom” by the side of “valor”
                    produces a kind of antithesis. And as Iphicrates said, “The path of my
                    words leads through the center of the deeds of Chares”; here the
                    metaphor is proportional and the words “through the center”
                    create vividness. Also, to say that one “calls upon dangers to help
                    against dangers” is a vivid metaphor. And Lycoleon on behalf of
                    Chabrias said, “not even reverencing the suppliant attitude of his
                    statue of bronze,”<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The statue of
                        Chabrias, erected after one of his victories, represented him as kneeling on
                        the ground, the position which he had ordered his soldiers to take up when
                        awaiting the enemy. The statue was in the agora and could be seen from the
                        court. Lycoleon points to it, and bases his appeal on its suppliant
                        attitude.
                    </note> a metaphor for the moment, not for all time, but still
                    vivid; for when Chabrias is in danger, the statue intercedes for him, the
                    inanimate becomes animate, the memorial of what he has done for the State. And
                    “in every way studying poorness of spirit,”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Isoc. 4.151" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Isoc.
                        4.151</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    for “studying” a thing implies to
                    increase it.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Metaphor from species to genus
                        (10.7, first note.), “studying” being
                        a species of “increasing.” As a rule one studies to
                        increase some good quality, not a bad one.
                    </note> And that “reason
                    is a light that God has kindled in the soul,” for both the words
                    reason and light make something clear. “For we do not put an end to
                    wars, but put them off,”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Isoc. 4.172" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Isoc. 4.172</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    for both ideas refer to the
                    future—putting off and a peace of such a kind. And again, it is a
                    metaphor to say that such a treaty is “a trophy far more splendid than
                    those gained in war; for the latter are raised in memory of trifling advantages
                    and a single favor of fortune, but the former commemorates the end of the whole
                    war”;
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                        <bibl n="Isoc. 4.180" default="NO" valid="yes">Isoc. 4.180</bibl>
                        (apparently from memory).
                    </note>
                    for both treaty and trophy are signs of victory. Again, that cities also
                    render<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>a heavy account to the censure of men; for
                    rendering an account
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign lang="greek">εὔθυνα</foreign>
                        (see 10.7, third note) further
                        implies the punishment for an unsatisfactory statement of accounts.
                    </note>
                    is a sort of just punishment.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="11"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>We have said
                    that smart sayings are derived from proportional metaphor and expressions which
                    set things before the eyes. We must now explain the meaning of “before
                    the eyes,” and what must be done to produce this.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>I mean that things
                    are set before the eyes by words
                    that signify actuality. For instance, to say that a good man is
                    “four-square”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Simonides, frag. 5 (<title>P.L.G.</title> 2.).
                        Both a
                        good man and a square are complete as far as they go, but they do not
                        express actuality.
                    </note>
                    is a metaphor, for both these are complete, but
                    the phrase does not express actuality, whereas “of one having the
                    prime of his life in full bloom”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Isoc. 5.10" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Isoc. 5.10</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    does; similarly,
                    “thee, like a sacred animal ranging at will”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Isoc. 5.127" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Isoc. 5.127</bibl>. This
                        speech is an appeal to Philip to lead the Greeks against <placeName key="tgn,7000231"
                                                                                            authname="tgn,7000231">
                            Persia</placeName>. As a sacred animal could roam
                        where it pleased within the precincts of its temple, so Philip could claim
                        the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> as his
                        fatherland, while other descendants of Heracles (whom Isocrates
                        calls the author of Philip's line) were tied down and their outlook
                        narrowed by the laws and constitution of the city in which they
                        dwelt.
                    </note>
                    expresses actuality, and in
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Thereupon the Greeks shooting forward with their feet
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Eur. IA 80" default="NO"
                                                                                             valid="yes">Eur. IA
                                    80</bibl>, with <foreign lang="greek">δορί</foreign> for
                                    <foreign lang="greek">ποσίν</foreign>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    the word “shooting” contains both actuality and
                    metaphor.<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>And as Homer often, by making use of
                    metaphor, speaks of inanimate things as if they were animate; and it is to
                    creating actuality in all such cases that his popularity is due, as in the
                    following examples:
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Again the ruthless stone rolled down to the plain.
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 11.598"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Od. 11.598</bibl>,
                                    with <foreign lang="greek">ἔπειτα πέδονδε</foreign> for
                                    <foreign lang="greek">ἐπὶ
                                        δάπεδόνδε</foreign>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>The arrow flew.
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 13.587"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Il. 13.587</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>[The arrow] eager to fly [towards the
                                crowd].
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 4.126"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Il. 4.126</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1412a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>[The spears] were buried in the ground, longing to
                                take their fill of flesh.
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 11.574"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Il. 11.574</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>The spear-point sped eagerly through his breast.
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 15.541"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Il.
                                    15.541</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    . For in all these examples there is appearance of actuality, since the
                    objects are represented as animate: “the shameless stone,”
                    “the eager spear-point,” and the rest express actuality.
                    Homer has attached these attributes by the employment of the proportional
                    metaphor; for as the stone is to Sisyphus, so is the shameless one to the one
                    who is shamelessly treated.<milestone unit="section" n="4"/>In his popular
                    similes also he proceeds in the same manner with inanimate things:
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Arched, foam-crested, some in front, others behind;
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 13.799"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Il.
                                    13.799</bibl>. The reference is to the “boiling
                                    waves of the loud-roaring sea.”
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    for he gives movement and life to all, and actuality is movement.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="5"/>As we have said before, metaphors should be
                    drawn from objects which are proper to the object, but not too obvious; just as,
                    for instance, in philosophy it needs sagacity to grasp the similarity in things
                    that are apart. Thus Archytas said that there was no difference between an
                    arbitrator and an altar, for the wronged betakes itself to one or the other.
                    Similarly, if one were to say that an anchor and a pot-hook hung up were
                    identical; for both are the same sort of thing, but they differ in
                    this—that one is hung up above and the other below.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The anchor keeps a ship steady <emph>
                        below</emph>, the pot
                        hook is <emph>above</emph>, and the pot hangs down from it.
                    </note>
                    And if
                    one were to say “the cities have been reduced to the same
                    level,” this amounts to the same in the case of things far
                    apart—the equality of “levelling” in regard to
                    superficies and resources.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Cope, retaining
                        <foreign lang="greek">ἀνωμαλίσθαι</foreign>
                        (as if from
                        <foreign lang="greek">ἀνομαλίζειν</foreign>, <emph>aequalitatem
                            restituere
                        </emph> Bonitz, cf. <foreign lang="greek">ἀνομάλωσις</foreign>) says: “the widely dissimilar
                        things here compared are the areas of properties and the state offices and
                        privileges, which are to be alike equalized,” translating:
                        “And the re-equalization of cities, when the same principle is
                        applied to things standing wide apart, viz. to surface
                        (area) and powers (functions,
                        offices).” ( <foreign lang="greek">ἀν-</foreign> is not negative, but = re.) But the passage
                        quoted
                        by Victorius from <bibl n="Isoc. 5.40" default="NO" valid="yes">Isoc. 5.40</bibl>: “for I
                        know that all the cities of
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>
                        have been placed on the same level ( <foreign lang="greek">ὡμαλίσθαι</foreign>) by misfortunes”
                        suggests this
                        as a preferable reading here,
                        <foreign lang="greek">ὡμαλίσθαι</foreign>
                        meaning (1) have been levelled to the ground
                        (although the Lexica give no instance of this use),
                        (2) reduced to the same level of weakness.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="6"/>Most smart sayings are derived from metaphor,<lb ed="Bekker"
                                                                                                     n="20"/>and also
                    from misleading the hearer beforehand.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><foreign lang="greek">προεξαπατᾶν</foreign>.
                        Or, reading <foreign lang="greek">προσεξαπατᾶν</foreign>, “by
                        adding deception.”
                    </note>
                    For it becomes more evident to him that
                    he has learnt something, when the conclusion turns out contrary to his
                    expectation, and the mind seems to say, “How true it is! but I missed
                    it.” And smart apophthegms arise from not meaning what one says, as in
                    the apophthegm of Stesichorus, that “the grasshoppers will sing to
                    themselves from the ground.”<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">See
                        2.21.8.
                    </note> And clever riddles are agreeable for the same reason; for
                    something is learnt, and the expression is also metaphorical. And what Theodorus
                    calls “novel expressions” arise when what follows is
                    paradoxical, and, as he puts it, not in accordance with our previous
                    expectation; just as humorists make use of slight changes in words. The same
                    effect is produced by jokes that turn on a change of letter; for they are
                    deceptive. These novelties occur in poetry as well as in prose; for instance,
                    the following verse does not finish as the hearer expected:
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>And he strode on, under his feet—chilblains,</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    whereas the hearer thought he was going to say
                    “sandals.” This kind of joke must be clear from the moment
                    of utterance. Jokes that turn on the word are produced, not by giving it the
                    proper meaning, but by perverting it; for instance, when Theodorus said to
                    Nicon, the player on the cithara, “you are troubled”
                    ( <foreign lang="greek">θράττει</foreign>); for while
                    pretending to say “something troubles you,” he deceives us;
                    for he means something else.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">According to
                        Cope, <foreign lang="greek">Θρᾷττ᾽ εἶ</foreign>, “you are no
                        better than a Thracian slave-girl.”
                    </note>
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1412b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>Therefore the joke is only
                    agreeable to one who understands the point; for if one does not know that Nicon
                    is a Thracian, he will not see any joke in it.<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>Similarly, “you wish
                    to destroy him ( <foreign lang="greek">πέρσαι</foreign>).”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">There is obviously a play on
                        <foreign lang="greek">πέρσαι</foreign>
                        (aor. 1 infin. of <foreign lang="greek">πέρθω</foreign>)
                        and <foreign lang="greek">Πέρσαι</foreign> (Persians),
                        but no satisfactory interpretation of the joke has been suggested.
                    </note>
                    Jokes of both these kinds<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The paradoxical and
                        verbal. “Suitably” may refer to the manner of delivery;
                        to being used at the proper time; or to taking care that the word is one
                        that may be used in the two senses.
                    </note> must be suitably expressed.
                    Similar instances are such witticisms as saying that “the empire of
                    the sea” was not “the beginning of misfortunes”
                    for the Athenians, for they benefited by it; or, with Isocrates,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Isoc. 5.61" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Isoc. 5.61</bibl>; <bibl
                            n="Isoc. 8.101" default="NO" valid="yes">Isoc. 8.101</bibl>. The point in the illustrations
                        lies
                        in the use of <foreign lang="greek">ἀρχή</foreign>, first in the sense of
                        “empire,” then in that of
                        “beginning.” It could be said that the
                        “empire” of the sea was or was not “the
                        beginning of misfortunes” for <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">
                            Athens</placeName>; for at first it was highly beneficial to them, but
                        in the end brought disaster, and thus was the
                        “beginning” of evil.
                    </note>
                    that
                    “empire” was “the beginning of misfortunes for the
                    city”; in both cases that which one would not have expected to be said
                    is said, and recognized as true. For, in the second example, to say that
                    “empire is empire” shows no cleverness, but this is not what
                    he means, but something else; in the first, the <foreign lang="greek">ἀρχή</foreign> which is
                    negatived is used in a different sense.<milestone unit="section" n="8"/>In all these cases, success
                    is attained when a word is
                    appropriately applied, either by homonym or by metaphor. For example, in the
                    phrase Anaschetos (Bearable) is Unbearable,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                        Usually translated, “There is no bearing
                        Baring.”
                    </note> there is a contradiction of the homonym, which is
                    only appropriate, if Anaschetus is an unbearable person. And, “Thou
                    shalt not be more of a stranger than a stranger,” or “not
                    more than you should be,” which is the same thing. And again,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>The stranger must not always be a stranger,</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    for here too the word repeated is taken in a different sense.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                        <persName>
                            <surname full="yes">Kock</surname>
                        </persName>
                        ,
                        <title>C.A.F.</title>
                        3.209, p. 448. In the two first examples
                        “stranger” refers to a distant and reserved manner, as
                        we say “don't make yourself a stranger”; in the third
                        <foreign lang="greek">ξένος</foreign>
                        is apparently to be taken in the
                        sense of “alien.” Cope translates: “for that
                        too is of a different kind” (foreign, alien to the two
                        others; <foreign lang="greek">ἀλλότριον</foreign>, belonging to something
                        or somebody else, opposed to <foreign lang="greek">οἰκεῖον</foreign>). But the whole passage is
                        obscure.
                    </note>
                    It
                    is the same with the celebrated verse of Anaxandrides,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>It is noble to die before doing anything that deserves death;
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                                    <persName>
                                        <surname full="yes">Kock</surname>
                                    </persName>
                                    , <title>C.A.F.</title> 2. Frag. 64, p.
                                    163.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    for this is the same as saying that “it is worthy to die when
                    one does not<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>deserve to die,” or, that
                    “it is worthy to die when one is not worthy of death,” or,
                    “when one does nothing that is worthy of death.”<milestone unit="section" n="9"/>Now the form of
                    expression of these sayings is the
                    same; but the more concisely and antithetically they are expressed, the greater
                    is their popularity. The reason is that antithesis is more instructive and
                    conciseness gives knowledge more rapidly.<milestone unit="section" n="10"/>Further, in order that
                    what is said may be true and not superficial, it must
                    always either apply to a particular person or be suitably expressed; for it is
                    possible for it to have one quality and not the other. For instance,
                    “One ought to die guiltless of any offence,” “The
                    worthy man should take a worthy woman to wife.” There is no smartness
                    in either of these expressions, but there will be if both conditions are
                    fulfilled: “It is worthy for a man to die, when he is not worthy of
                    death.” The more special qualities the expression possesses, the
                    smarter it appears; for instance, if the words contain a metaphor, and a
                    metaphor of a special kind, antithesis, and equality of clauses, and actuality.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="11"/>Similes also, as said above, are always in a
                    manner approved metaphors;
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Or, reading
                        <foreign lang="greek">αἱ</foreign>
                        for <foreign lang="greek">ἀεὶ</foreign>, “approved similes are . . .”
                    </note>
                    since they always consist of two terms, like the proportional metaphor, as when
                    we say, for instance, that the shield is the goblet of Ares, and the bow a lyre
                    without strings.
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1413a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>But such an
                    expression is not simple, but when we call the bow a lyre, or the shield a
                    goblet, it is.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">In the simple metaphor
                        “goblet” is substituted for
                        “shield,” but sometimes additions are made to the word
                        as differently applied, such as “of Ares” and
                        “without strings.” These additions, besides involving
                        greater detail (a characteristic of the simile),
                        distinctly bring out the contrast of the two terms and make a simile,
                        whereas the metaphor simply transfers the meaning.
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="12"/>And similes may be formed as follows: a
                    flute-player resembles an ape,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">In
                        posture.
                    </note> a short-sighted man a spluttering lamp; for in both cases there
                    is contraction.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Contraction of eyelids and
                        flame.
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="13"/>But they are excellent when there is a
                    proportional metaphor; for it is possible to liken a shield to the goblet of
                    Ares and a ruin to the rag of a house; to say that Niceratus is a Philoctetes
                    bitten by Pratys, to use the simile of Thrasymachus, when he saw Niceratus,
                    defeated by Pratys in a rhapsodic competition, still dirty with his hair
                    uncut.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Like Philoctetes on <placeName
                            key="tgn,7011173" authname="tgn,7011173">Lemnos
                    </placeName> after he had been bitten by the
                        snake.
                    </note>
                    It is herein that poets are especially condemned if they fail,
                    but applauded if they succeed. I mean, for instance, when they introduce an
                    answering clause:
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">When the concluding
                        corresponds with the introductory expression. This “answering
                        clause” is called apodosis (5.2), not
                        restricted, as in modern usage, to the conclusion of a conditional sentence.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>He carries his legs twisted like parsley,</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    or again,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Like Philammon punching the leather sack.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    All such expressions are similes, and similes, as has been often said,
                    are metaphors of a kind.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="14"/>Proverbs also are metaphors from species to
                    species. If a man, for instance, introduces into his house something from which
                    he expects to benefit, but afterwards finds himself injured instead, it is as
                    the Carpathian
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Or, “he says it is a
                        case of the Carpathian and the hare.” An inhabitant of the island
                        of <placeName key="tgn,7016628" authname="tgn,7016628">Carpathus</placeName> introduced a brace
                        of
                        hares, which so multiplied that they devoured all the crops and ruined the
                        farmers (like the rabbits in <placeName key="tgn,7000490" authname="tgn,7000490">
                            Australia</placeName>).
                    </note>
                    says of the hare; for both have<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>experienced the same misfortunes. This is
                    nearly all
                    that can be said of the sources of smart sayings and the reasons which make them
                    so.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="15"/>Approved hyperboles are also metaphors. For
                    instance, one may say of a man whose eye is all black and blue, “you
                    would have thought he was a basket of mulberries,” because the black
                    eye is something purple, but the great quantity constitutes the hyperbole.
                    Again, when one says “like this or that” there is a
                    hyperbole differing only in the wording:
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Like Philammon punching the leather sack,</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    or, “you would have thought that he was Philammon fighting
                    the sack”;
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Carrying his legs twisted like parsley,</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    or, “you would have thought that he had no legs, but parsley,
                    they being so twisted.” There is something youthful about hyperboles;
                    <milestone unit="section" n="16"/>for they show vehemence. Wherefore those
                    who are in a passion most frequently make use of them:
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Not even were he to offer me gifts as many in number as the sand and
                                dust. . . but a daughter of Agamemnon, son of Atreus, I will not
                                wed, not even if she rivalled golden Aphrodite in beauty, or Athene
                                in accomplishments.
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 9.385"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Il. 9.385</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1413b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>(Attic orators are
                    especially fond of hyperbole.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">This must be
                        taken as a parenthetical remark, if it is Aristotle's at
                        all.</note>) Wherefore<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Because they
                        are boyish.
                    </note> it is unbecoming for elderly people to make use of them.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="12"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>But we must
                    not lose sight of the fact that a different style is suitable to each kind of
                    Rhetoric. That of written compositions is not the same as that of debate; nor,
                    in the latter, is that of public speaking the same as that of the law courts.
                    But it is necessary to be acquainted with both; for the one requires a knowledge
                    of good Greek, while the other prevents the necessity of keeping silent when we
                    wish to communicate something to others, which happens to those who do not know
                    how to write.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>The style of written compositions
                    is most precise, that of debate is most suitable for delivery. Of the latter
                    there are two kinds, ethical and emotional; this is why actors are always
                    running after plays of this character, and poets after suitable actors. However,
                    poets whose works are only meant for reading are also popular, as Chaeremon, who
                    is as precise as a writer of speeches, and Licymnius<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes"
                                                                              place="unspecified">See 2.13 of this book.
                </note> among dithyrambic poets. When
                    compared, the speeches of writers appear meagre in public debates, while those
                    of the rhetoricians, however well delivered, are amateurish when read. The
                    reason is that they are only suitable to public debates; hence speeches suited
                    for delivery, when delivery is absent, do not fulfil their proper function and
                    appear silly. For instance, asyndeta and frequent<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>repetition of the same word
                    are rightly disapproved in written speech, but in
                    public debate even rhetoricians make use of them, for they lend themselves to
                    acting.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">What follows, to the end of sect.
                        3, is of the nature of a parenthesis, not immediately connected with the
                        subject of the chapter.
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>
                    (But one must vary the expression
                    when one repeats the same thing, for this as it were paves the way for
                    declamation:<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The variation in the form of
                    the expression suggests a similar variation in the form of the delivery or
                    declamation.
                </note> as, “This is he who robbed you, this is he who
                    deceived you, this is he who at last attempted to betray you.” This is
                    what Philemon the actor did in <title>The Old Man's Folly</title> of
                    Anaxandrides, when he says “Rhadamanthus and Palamedes,” and
                    when he repeats the word “I” in the prologue to <title>The
                    Pious</title>.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The meaning of this has not
                    been satisfactorily explained. On the face of it, it seems to mean that the
                    excellence of Philemon's delivery consisted in his way of declaiming
                    passages in which the same words were repeated. Philemon is not to be
                    confused with the writer of the New Comedy, the rival and contemporary of
                    Menander.
                </note> For unless such expressions are varied by action, it is a
                    case of “the man who carries the beam”<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Used of
                    a stiff, ungraceful speaker.
                </note> in the
                    proverb.)
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="4"/>It is the same with asyndeta: “I came,
                    I met, I entreated.” For here delivery is needed, and the words should
                    not be pronounced with the same tone and character, as if there was only one
                    clause. Further, asyndeta have a special characteristic; for in an equal space
                    of time many things appear to be said, because the connecting particle makes
                    many things one, so that, if it be removed, it is clear that the contrary will
                    be the case, and that the one will become many. Therefore an asyndeton produces
                    amplification: thus, in “I came, I conversed, I besought,”
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1414a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>the hearer seems to be
                    surveying many things, all that the speaker said.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Spengel's reading here is: <foreign
                            lang="greek">πολλὰ
                        δοκεῖ: “ὑπερεῖδεν ὅσα εἶπον,” πολλὰ
                        δοκεῖ
                    </foreign> being parenthetical, and <foreign lang="greek">ὑπερεῖδον
                        ὅσα εἶπον
                    </foreign> part of the quotation. Jebb translates:
                        “I came, I spoke to him, I besought” (these
                        seem <emph>many</emph> things); “he disregarded all I
                        said” （which certainly gives a more natural sense to
                        <foreign lang="greek">ὑπερεῖδον</foreign>).
                    </note>
                    This also
                    is Homer's intention in the passage
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Nireus, again, from <placeName key="tgn,1008845" authname="tgn,1008845">Syme</placeName> .
                                .
                                .,
                            </l>
                            <l>Nireus son of Aglaia . . .,</l>
                            <l>Nireus, the most beautiful . . . ;
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                                    <bibl n="Hom. Il. 2.671" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.671 ff.</bibl>
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    for it is necessary that one of whom much has been said should be often
                    mentioned; if then the name is often mentioned, it seems as if much has been
                    said
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Cope translates: “they
                        think that, if the name is often repeated, there <emph>must be a great deal
                            to say
                        </emph> about its owner”; but can this be got out of the
                        Greek （ <foreign lang="greek">εἰρῆσθαι</foreign>)?
                    </note>
                    ; so that, by means of this fallacy,
                    Homer has increased the reputation of Nireus, though he only mentions him in one
                    passage; he has perpetuated his memory, though he never speaks of him again.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="5"/>The deliberative style is exactly like a rough
                    sketch,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Intended to produce the effect of
                        finished work at a distance before a large number of spectators.
                    </note> for
                    the greater the crowd, the further off is the point of view; wherefore in both
                    too much refinement is a superfluity and even a disadvantage. But the forensic
                    style is more finished, and more so before a single judge, because there is
                    least opportunity of employing rhetorical devices, since the mind more readily
                    takes in at a glance what belongs to the subject and what is foreign to it;
                    there is no discussion,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The meaning apparently
                        is that there is no discussion, as might be the case when there were several
                        judges, so that the decision is clear and unbiased. <foreign lang="greek">ἀγών</foreign> and <foreign
                                lang="greek">ἀγωνιστικὴ
                            λέξις
                        </foreign> are terms used for debate （e.g. in the law
                        courts) and the style suited to it （cf sect. 1).
                        Cope's editor refers to <bibl n="Cic. Att. 1.16.8" default="NO" valid="yes">Cic. Ad Att.
                            1.16.8
                        </bibl> “remoto illo studio contentionis, quem vos
                        [you Athenians]
                        <foreign lang="greek">ἀγῶνα</foreign>
                        appellatis.” Jebb translates: “the turmoil is absent, so
                        that the judgement is serene” （in a note,
                        “unclouded”).
                    </note>
                    so the judgement is clear.
                    This is why the same orators do not excel in all these styles; where action is
                    most effective, there the style is least finished, and this is a case in which
                    voice, especially a loud one, is needed.
                </p>
                <p>The epideictic style is especially suited to written compositions, for its
                    function is reading;
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">This does not seem to
                        agree with the general view. Funeral orations of the nature of panegyrics,
                        for instance, were certainly meant to be spoken; but the <foreign lang="greek">ἔργον</foreign> or
                        proper function of an epideictic may
                        be said to consist in reading, in its being agreeable to read. Its <foreign lang="greek">τέλος
                        </foreign> or end is to be read.
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="6"/>and next to it comes the forensic style. It is
                    superfluous to make the further distinction<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>that style
                    should be pleasant or magnificent. Why so, any more than temperate, liberal, or
                    anything else that indicates moral virtue? For it is evident that, if virtue of
                    style has been correctly defined, what we have said will suffice to make it
                    pleasant. For why, if not to please, need it be clear, not mean, but
                    appropriate? If it be too diffuse, or too concise, it will not be clear; but it
                    is plain that the mean is most suitable. What we have said will make the style
                    pleasant, if it contains a happy mixture of proper and
                    “foreign” words, of rhythm, and of persuasiveness resulting
                    from propriety. This finishes what we had to say about style; of all the three
                    kinds of Rhetoric in general, and of each of them in particular. It only remains
                    to speak of arrangement.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="13"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>A speech has
                    two parts. It is necessary to state the subject, and then to prove it. Wherefore
                    it is impossible to make a statement without proving it, or to prove it without
                    first putting it forward; for both he who proves proves something, and he who
                    puts something forward does so in order to prove it.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>The first of
                    these parts is the statement of the case, the second the
                    proof, a similar division to that of problem and demonstration.<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>But
                    the division now generally made is absurd; for
                    narrative only belongs in a manner to forensic speech, but in epideictic or
                    deliberative speech how is it possible that there should be narrative as it is
                    defined, or a refutation;
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1414b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>or
                    an epilogue in demonstrative speeches?
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The
                        generally accepted divisions are:
                        <foreign lang="greek">προοίμιον</foreign>
                        （exordium),
                        <foreign lang="greek">διήγησις</foreign>
                        （narrative),
                        <foreign lang="greek">πίστις</foreign>
                        （proof),
                        <foreign lang="greek">ἐπίλογος</foreign>
                        （peroration). （ <foreign lang="greek">διήγησις</foreign> is a species of <foreign lang="greek">
                            πρόθεσις</foreign>, which is used instead of it just before.)
                        Aristotle objects that it is （as a rule) only the forensic
                        speech which requires a regular <foreign lang="greek">διήγησις</foreign>, a
                        full and detailed statement of what has happened before. In epideictic and
                        demonstrative （deliberative) speeches, the object of which
                        is to prove something, there is no need of another existing division called
                        the refutation of the adversary, and in the demonstrative there can be no
                        room for an epilogue, which is not a summary of <emph>proofs and
                            arguments</emph>. Thus the necessary divisions of a speech are really only
                        two; <foreign lang="greek">πρόθεσις</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">πίστις</foreign>, or at
                        most four.
                    </note>
                    In deliberative speeches,
                    again, exordium, comparison, and recapitulation are only admissible when there
                    is a conflict of opinion. For both accusation and defence are often found in
                    deliberative, but not <emph>qua</emph> deliberative speech. And further, the
                    epilogue does not even belong to every forensic speech, for instance, when it is
                    short, or the matter is easy to recollect; for in the epilogue what happens is
                    that there is a reduction of length.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">i.e. its
                        use is to recall the main facts briefly （sect. 4 end),
                        which in a short speech is needless.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="4"/>So then the necessary parts of a speech are the
                    statement of the case and proof. These divisions are appropriate to every
                    speech, and at the most the parts are four in number—exordium,
                    statement, proof, epilogue; for refutation of an opponent is part of the proofs,
                    and comparison is an amplification of one's own case, and therefore also part of
                    the proofs; for he who does this proves something, whereas the exordium and the
                    epilogue are merely aids to memory.<milestone unit="section" n="5"/>Therefore,
                    if we adopt all such divisions we shall be following Theodorus
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Plat. Phaedrus 266d" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Plat. Phaedrus
                        266d</bibl>, where the additional kinds of narrative are omitted, and
                        their place taken by <foreign lang="greek">πίστωσις</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">
                            ἐπιπίστωσις
                        </foreign> （confirmation of the
                        proof).
                    </note>
                    and his school, who distinguished narrative,
                    additional narrative, and preliminary narrative, refutation and additional
                    refutation. But one must only adopt a name to express a distinct species or a
                    real difference; otherwise, it becomes empty and silly, like the terms
                    introduced by Licymnius in his “Art,” where he speaks of
                    “being wafted along,” “wandering from the
                    subject,”<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Or,
                        “diverting the judge's attention.”
                    </note> and
                    “ramifications.”
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="14"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>The exordium
                    is the beginning of a speech, as<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>the prologue in poetry
                    and the prelude in flute-playing; for all these are beginnings, and as it were a
                    paving the way for what follows. The prelude resembles the exordium of
                    epideictic speeches; for as flute-players begin by playing whatever they can
                    execute skilfully and attach it to the key-note, so also in epideictic speeches
                    should be the composition of the exordium; the speaker should say at once
                    whatever he likes, give the key-note and then attach the main subject. And all
                    do this, an example being the exordium of the <title>Helen</title> of Isocrates;
                    for the eristics and Helen have nothing in common.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The subject of the oration was the praise of
                        Helen, but
                        Isocrates took the opportunity of attacking the sophists. This exemplifies
                        his skill in the introduction of matter not strictly proper to, or in common
                        with, the subject. The key-note is Helen; but the exordium is an attack on
                        the Eristics, with special allusion to the Cynics and the Megarians.
                    </note>
                    At the same time, even if the speaker wanders from the point, this is more
                    appropriate than that the speech should be monotonous.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="2"/>In epideictic speeches, the sources of the
                    exordia are praise and blame, as Gorgias, in the
                    <title>Olympiacus,</title>
                    says, “Men of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, you are
                    worthy to be admired by many,” where he is praising those who
                    instituted the solemn assemblies. Isocrates on the other hand blames them
                    because they rewarded bodily excellences, but instituted no prize for men of
                    wisdom.<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>Exordia may also be derived from
                    advice, for instance, one should honor the good, wherefore the speaker praises
                    Aristides, or such as are neither famous nor worthless, but who, although they
                    are good, remain obscure, as Alexander, son of Priam;
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1415a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>for this is a piece of advice.<milestone unit="section" n="4"/>Again, they
                    may be derived from forensic exordia, that
                    is to say, from appeals to the hearer, if the subject treated is paradoxical,
                    difficult, or commonly known, in order to obtain indulgence, like Choerilus
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Of <placeName key="tgn,7002673"
                                                                                         authname="tgn,7002673">
                        Samos</placeName>, epic poet, author of a poem on the Persian war, from
                        which this half-line and the context preserved in the Scholiast are taken.
                        He complains that whereas the poets of olden times had plenty to write
                        about, the field of poetry being as yet untilled, it was now all
                        apportioned, and he, the last of the poets, was left behind, unable to find
                        “a new chariot for the race-course of his song.
                        ”
                    </note>
                    :
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>But now when all has been allotted.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    These then are the sources of epideictic exordia—praise,
                    blame, exhortation, dissuasion, appeals to the hearer. And these exordia
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign lang="greek">ἐνδόσιμα</foreign>
                        =
                        <foreign lang="greek">προοίμια</foreign>.
                    </note>
                    may be either foreign
                    or intimately connected with the speech.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="5"/>As for the exordia of the forensic speech, it
                    must be noted that they produce the same effect as dramatic prologues and epic
                    exordia （for those of dithyrambs resemble epideictic exordia:
                    <quote>For thee and thy presents or spoils).
                        <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">A parenthetical remark to the effect that
                            epideictic
                            exordia are different. Those of a forensic speech are like prologues and
                            epic exordia, but it is different with epideictic, which may be wild,
                            high-flown, as in the example given from an unknown author.
                        </note>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="6"/>But in speeches
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">That is, forensic speeches. <foreign
                            lang="greek">δράμασι
                    </foreign> has been suggested for <foreign lang="greek">λόγοις</foreign>.
                    </note>
                    and epic poems the exordia provide a sample of
                    the subject, in order that the hearers may know beforehand what it is about, and
                    that the mind may not be kept in suspense, for that which is undefined leads
                    astray; so then he who puts the beginning, so to say, into the hearer's hand
                    enables him, if he holds fast to it, to follow the story. Hence the following
                    exordia:
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Sing the wrath, O Muse.
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 1.1"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Il 1.1</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Tell me of the man, O Muse.
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 1.1"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Od. 1.1</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Inspire me with another theme, how from the land of <placeName key="tgn,1000004"
                                                                                              authname="tgn,1000004">
                                Asia
                            </placeName> a great war crossed into
                                <placeName key="tgn,1000003" authname="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName>.
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">From Choerilus （sect.
                                    4).
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    Similarly, tragic poets make clear the subject of their drama, if not
                    at the outset,<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>like Euripides, at least somewhere in the
                    prologue, like Sophocles,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>My father was Polybus.
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Soph. OT 774"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Soph. OT 774</bibl>. But this can hardly be
                                    called the prologue.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    It is the same in comedy. So then the most essential and special
                    function of the exordium is to make clear what is the end or purpose of the
                    speech; wherefore it should not be employed, if the subject is quite clear or
                    unimportant.<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>All the other forms of exordia in
                    use are only remedies,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">That is, special
                        remedies in the case of the hearers suffering from “inattention,
                        unfavorable disposition, and the like”
                        （Cope).
                    </note> and are common to all three branches of
                    Rhetoric. These are derived from the speaker, the hearer, the subject, and the
                    opponent. From the speaker and the opponent, all that helps to destroy or create
                    prejudice. But this must not be done in the same way; for the defendant must
                    deal with this at the beginning, the accuser in the epilogue. The reason is
                    obvious. The defendant, when about to introduce himself, must remove all
                    obstacles, so that he must first clear away all prejudice; the accuser must
                    create prejudice in the epilogue, that his hearers may have a livelier
                    recollection of it.
                </p>
                <p>The object of an appeal to the hearer is to make him well disposed or to arouse
                    his indignation, and sometimes to engage his attention or the opposite; for it
                    is not always expedient to engage his attention, which is the reason why many
                    speakers try to make their hearers laugh. As for rendering the hearers
                    tractable, everything will lead up to it if a person wishes, including the
                    appearance of respectability,
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1415b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>because respectable persons command more attention. Hearers pay most
                    attention
                    to things that are important, that concern their own interests, that are
                    astonishing, that are agreeable; wherefore one should put the idea into their
                    heads that the speech deals with such subjects. To make his hearers inattentive,
                    the speaker must persuade them that the matter is unimportant, that it does not
                    concern them, that it is painful.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="8"/>But we must not lose sight of the fact that all
                    such things are outside the question, for they are only addressed to a hearer
                    whose judgement is poor and who is ready to listen to what is beside the case;
                    for if he is not a man of this kind, there is no need of an exordium, except
                    just to make a summary statement of the subject, so that, like a body, it may
                    have a head.<milestone unit="section" n="9"/>Further, engaging the hearers'
                    attention is common to all parts of the speech, if necessary; for attention
                    slackens everywhere else rather than at the beginning. Accordingly, it is
                    ridiculous to put this<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">i.e., to claim the
                        hearer's attention at the beginning, for every one is keen to listen then,
                        but later on attention slackens.
                    </note> at the beginning, at a time when all
                    listen with the greatest attention. Wherefore, when the right moment comes, one
                    must say, “And give me your attention, for it concerns you as much as
                    myself”; and, “I will tell you such a thing as you have
                    never yet” heard of, so strange and wonderful. This is what Prodicus
                    used to do; whenever his hearers began to nod, he would throw in a dash of his
                    fifty-drachma lecture.<milestone unit="section" n="10"/>But it is clear that
                    one does not speak thus to the hearer <emph>qua</emph> hearer;
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The hearer <emph>qua</emph> hearer should be
                        unbiased, but in fact hearers often suffer from the defects referred to in
                        sect. 7, for which certain forms of exordia are remedies.
                    </note>
                    for all in
                    their exordia endeavor either to arouse prejudice or to remove their own
                    apprehensions:
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>O prince, I will not say that with haste [I have come
                                breathless].
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Soph. Ant. 223"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Soph. Ant. 223</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Why this preamble?
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Eur. IT 1162"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Eur. IT 1162</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    This is what those also do who have, or seem to have, a bad case; for
                    it is better to lay stress upon anything rather than the case itself. That is
                    why slaves never answer questions directly but go all round them, and indulge in
                    preambles.<milestone unit="section" n="11"/>We have stated<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes"
                                                                                    place="unspecified">2.1.7, 8.
                    </note> how the hearer's goodwill is to be secured
                    and all other similar states of mind. And since it is rightly said,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Grant that on reaching the Phaeacians I may find friendship or
                                compassion,
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 7.327"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Od. 7.327</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    the orator should aim at exciting these two feelings.
                </p>
                <p>In epideictic exordia, one must make the hearer believe that he shares the
                    praise, either himself, or his family, or his pursuits, or at any rate in some
                    way or other. For
                    <persName>
                        <surname full="yes">Socrates</surname>
                    </persName>
                    says truly in his Funeral Oration that “it
                    is easy to praise Athenians in the presence of Athenians, but not in the
                    presence of Lacedaemonians.”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">See
                        1.9.30.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="12"/>Deliberative oratory borrows its exordia from
                    forensic, but naturally they are very uncommon in it. For in fact the hearers
                    are acquainted with the subject, so that the case needs no exordium, except for
                    the orator's own sake, or on account of his adversaries, or if the hearers
                    attach too much or too little importance to the question according to his idea.
                    Wherefore he must either excite or remove prejudice, and magnify or minimize the
                    importance of the subject. Such are the reasons for exordia; or else they merely
                    serve the purpose of ornament,
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1416a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>since their absence makes the speech appear offhand. For such is the encomium
                    on the Eleans, in which Gorgias, without any preliminary sparring or movements,
                    starts off at once, “<placeName key="perseus,Elis" authname="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName>,
                    happy city.”
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="15"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>One way of
                    removing prejudice is to make use of the arguments by which one may clear
                    oneself from disagreeable suspicion; for it makes no difference whether this
                    suspicion has been openly expressed or not; and so this may be taken as a
                    general rule.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>Another way
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Another reading is
                        <foreign lang="greek">τόπος</foreign>
                        （topic) and so throughout.
                    </note>
                    consists in contesting
                    the disputed points, either by denying the fact or its harmfulness, at least to
                    the plaintiff; or by asserting that its importance is exaggerated; or that it is
                    not unjust at all, or only slightly so; or neither disgraceful nor important.
                    These are the possible points of dispute: as Iphicrates, in answer to
                    Nausicrates, admitted that he had done what the prosecutor alleged and inflicted
                    damage, but denied that he had been guilty of wrongdoing. Again, one may strike
                    the balance, when guilty of wrongdoing, by maintaining that although the action
                    was injurious it was honorable, painful but useful, or anything else of the
                    kind.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="3"/>Another method consists in saying that it was a
                    case of error, misfortune, or necessity; as, for example, Sophocles said that he
                    trembled, not, as the accuser said, in order to appear old, but from necessity,
                    for it was against his wish that he was eighty years of age.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Sophocles had two sons, Iophon and Ariston,
                        by different
                        wives; the latter had a son named Sophocles. Iophon, jealous of the
                        affection shown by Sophocles to this grandson, summoned him before the
                        <emph>phratores</emph>
                        （a body which had some jurisdiction in
                        family affairs) on the ground that his age rendered him incapable
                        of managing his affairs. In reply to the charge, Sophocles read the famous
                        choric ode on <placeName key="tgn,7002681" authname="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> from the
                        <title>Oedipus Coloneus</title>, beginning <foreign lang="greek">Εὐίππου, ξένε, τᾶσδε χώρας
                        </foreign> （<bibl n="Soph. OC 668" default="NO" valid="yes">Soph. OC 668 ff.</bibl>), and was
                        acquitted. The story in this form is probably derived from some comedy,
                        which introduced the case on the stage （see Jebb's Introd. to the
                        tragedy).
                    </note>
                    One may also substitute one motive for another,
                    and say that one did not mean to injure but to do something else, not that of
                    which one was accused, and that the wrongdoing was accidental: “I
                    should deserve<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>your hatred, had I acted so as to bring
                    this about.”
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="4"/>Another method may be employed if the accuser,
                    either himself or one closely related to him, has been involved in a similar
                    charge, either now or formerly;<milestone unit="section" n="5"/>or, if others
                    are involved who are admittedly not exposed to the charge; for instance, if it
                    is argued that so-and-so is an adulterer, because he is a dandy, then so-and-so
                    must be.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="6"/>Again, if the accuser has already similarly
                    accused others, or himself been accused by others;
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">In the reading in the text, <foreign
                            lang="greek">αὐτούς
                    </foreign> must apparently refer to the defendant, and one would
                        rather expect <foreign lang="greek">αὐτόν</foreign>. Spengel suggested
                        <foreign lang="greek">ἢ ἄλλος ἢ αὐτός</foreign>
                        for <foreign lang="greek">ἢ ἄλλος αὐτούς</foreign>: if he （i.e. the
                        adversary) or another has similarly accused others.
                    </note>
                    or if
                    others, without being formally accused, have been suspected as you are now, and
                    their innocence has been proved.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="7"/>Another method consists in counter-attacking the
                    accuser; for it would be absurd to believe the words of one who is himself
                    unworthy of belief.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="8"/>Another method is to appeal to a verdict already
                    given, as Euripides did in the case about the exchange of property;<note resp="Freese"
                                                                                             anchored="yes"
                                                                                             place="unspecified">When a
                        citizen was called upon to perform a
                        “liturgy” or public service （e.g. the equipment
                        of a chorus), if he thought that one richer than himself had been
                        passed over he could summon him and compel him to exchange
                        properties.
                    </note> when Hygiaenon accused him of impiety as having advised
                    perjury in the verse,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>My tongue hath sworn, but my mind is unsworn,
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Eur. Hipp. 612"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Eur. Hipp. 612</bibl>.
                                    This well-known verse is three times parodied in Aristophanes
                                    （<bibl n="Aristoph. Thes. 275" default="NO" valid="yes">Aristoph. Thes.
                                        275</bibl>; <bibl n="Aristoph. Frogs 101" default="NO" valid="yes">Aristoph.
                                        Frogs
                                        101</bibl>, <bibl n="Aristoph. Frogs 1471" default="NO" valid="yes">Aristoph.
                                        Frogs1471</bibl>). In the first passage, the sense is
                                    reversed: Euripides has dressed up a certain Mnesilochus as a
                                    woman in order that he may attend the Thesmophorian assembly.
                                    Mnesilochus first requires Euripides to take an oath that he
                                    will help him out of any trouble that may arise. Euripides takes
                                    an oath by all the gods, whereupon Mnesilochus says to
                                    Euripides: “Remember that it was your mind that swore,
                                    but not your tongue.” When Euripides was engaged in a
                                    lawsuit, his adversary quoted the line, implying that even on
                                    oath Euripides could not be believed; Euripides replied that his
                                    adversary had no right to bring before the law courts a matter
                                    which had already been settled by the theatrical
                                    judges.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    Euripides replied that his accuser did wrong in transferring the
                    decisions of the court of Dionysus to the law courts; for he had already
                    rendered an account of what he had said there,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes"
                                                                        place="unspecified">In the great Dionysiac
                        theater.
                    </note> or was still ready to do so, if his
                    adversary desired to accuse him.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="9"/>Another method consists in attacking slander,
                    showing how great an evil it is, and this because it alters the nature of
                    judgements,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Or, “makes
                        extraneous points the subject of decision”
                        （Cope), “raises false issues”
                        （Jebb).
                    </note> and that it does not rely on the real facts
                    of the case.
                </p>
                <p>Common to both parties is the topic of tokens,
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1416b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>as in the <title>Teucer</title>,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes"
                                                                                 place="unspecified">Of Sophocles.
                    </note> Odysseus reproaches Teucer with being a
                    relative of Priam, whose sister his mother Hesione was; to which Teucer replied
                    that his father Telamon was the enemy of Priam, and that he himself did not
                    denounce the spies.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Who had been sent to
                        <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>
                        by the Greeks to spy upon
                        the Trojans. It seems that he was afterwards accused of treachery, the
                        <emph>token</emph>
                        being the fact that Teucer was a near connection of
                        Priam; to which he replied with another <emph>token</emph> that his father
                        was an enemy of Priam, and further, when the Greek spies were in <placeName key="perseus,Troy"
                                                                                                    authname="perseus,Troy">
                            Troy</placeName>, he never betrayed them.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="10"/>Another method, suitable for the accuser, is to
                    praise something unimportant at great length, and to condemn something important
                    concisely; or, putting forward several things that are praiseworthy in the
                    opponent, to condemn the one thing that has an important bearing upon the case.
                    Such methods
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Jebb refers <foreign lang="greek">τοιοῦτοι
                    </foreign> to the accusers, translating <foreign lang="greek">τεχνικοί</foreign> “artistic,”
                        certainly the
                        commoner meaning.
                    </note>
                    are most artful and unfair; for by their use men
                    endeavor to make what is good in a man injurious to him, by mixing it up with
                    what is bad.
                </p>
                <p>Another method is common to both accuser and defender. Since the same thing may
                    have been done from several motives, the accuser must disparage it by taking it
                    in the worse sense, while the defender must take it in the better sense. For
                    instance, when Diomedes chose Odysseus for his companion, it may be said on the
                    one hand that he did so because he considered him to be the bravest of men, on
                    the other, that it was because Odysseus was the only man who was no possible
                    rival for him, since he was a poltroon. Let this suffice for the question of
                    prejudice.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="16"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>In the
                    epideictic style the narrative should not be consecutive, but disjointed; for it
                    is necessary to go through the actions which form the subject of the speech. For
                    a speech is made up of one part that is inartificial （the speaker being
                    in no way the author<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>of the actions which he
                    relates), and of another that does depend upon art. The latter consists
                    in showing that the action did take place, if it be incredible, or that it is of
                    a certain kind, or of a certain importance, or all three together.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
                    This is why it is sometimes right not to narrate all
                    the facts consecutively, because a demonstration of this kind<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes"
                                                                                       place="unspecified">Involving a
                    continuous succession of proofs.
                </note> is
                    difficult to remember. From some facts a man may be shown to be courageous, from
                    others wise or just. Besides, a speech of this kind is simpler, whereas the
                    other is intricate and not plain.<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>It is only
                    necessary to recall famous actions; wherefore most people have no need of
                    narrative—for instance, if you wish to praise Achilles; for everybody
                    knows what he did, and it is only necessary to make use of it. But if you wish
                    to praise Critias, narrative is necessary, for not many people know what he did
                    . . .
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Something has been lost here, as is
                        shown by the transition from epideictic to forensic Rhetoric. All the mss.
                        have a gap, which in several of them is filled by introducing the passage
                        <foreign lang="greek">ἔστι δ᾽ ἔπαινος . . . μετατεθῇ</foreign>
                        （1.9.33-37).
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="4"/>But at the present day it is absurdly laid down
                    that the narrative should be rapid. And yet, as the man said to the baker when
                    he asked whether he was to knead bread hard or soft, “What! is it
                    impossible to knead it well?” so it is in this case; for the narrative
                    must not be long, nor the exordium, nor the proofs either. For in this case also
                    propriety does not consist either in rapidity or conciseness, but in a due mean;
                    that is, one must say all that will make the facts clear,
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1417a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>or create the belief that they have
                    happened or have done injury or wrong, or that they are as important as you wish
                    to make them. The opposite party must do the opposite.<milestone unit="section" n="5"/>And you
                    should incidentally narrate anything that tends to show your
                    own virtue, for instance, “I always recommended him to act rightly,
                    not to forsake his children”; or the wickedness of your opponent, for
                    instance, “but he answered that, wherever he might be, he would always
                    find other children,” an answer attributed by Herodotus
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hdt. 2.30" default="NO" valid="yes">
                        Hdt. 2.30</bibl>. The story
                        was that a number of Egyptian soldiers had revolted and left in a body for
                        <placeName key="tgn,7000489" authname="tgn,7000489">Ethiopia</placeName>. Their king
                        Psammetichus begged them not to desert their wives and children, to which
                        one of them made answer （ <foreign lang="greek">τῶν δέ τινα
                            λέγεται δέξαντα τὸ αἰδοῖον εἰπεῖν, ἔνθα ἂν τοῦτο ᾖ,
                            ἔσεσθαι αὐτοῖσι ἐνθαῦτα καὶ τέκνα καὶ
                            γυναῖκας</foreign>).
                    </note>
                    to the Egyptian rebels; or anything
                    which is likely to please the dicasts.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="6"/>In defence, the narrative need not be so long;
                    for the points at issue are either that the fact has not happened or that it was
                    neither injurious nor wrong nor so important as asserted, so that one should not
                    waste time over what all are agreed upon, unless anything tends to prove that,
                    admitting the act, it is not wrong.<milestone unit="section" n="7"/>Again, one
                    should only mention such past things as are likely to excite pity or indignation
                    if described as actually happening; for instance, the story of Alcinous, because
                    in the presence of Penelope it is reduced to sixty lines,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 23.264-284" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Hom. Od. 23.264-284</bibl>,
                        <bibl n="Hom. Od. 23.310-343" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Od. 23.310-343</bibl>. The title
                        referred to the narrative in Books 9-12. It became proverbial for a
                        long-winded story.
                    </note>
                    and the way in which Phayllus dealt with the epic
                    cycle,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">he apparently summarized it.</note>
                    and the prologue to the <title>Oeneus</title>.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Of Euripides. It was apparently very
                        compact.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="8"/>And the narrative should be of a moral
                    character, and in fact it will be so, if we know what effects this. One thing is
                    to make clear our moral purpose; for as is the moral purpose, so is the
                    character, and as is the end, so is the moral purpose. For this reason
                    mathematical treatises have no<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>moral character, because
                    neither have they moral purpose; for they have no moral end. But the Socratic
                    dialogues have; for they discuss such questions.<milestone unit="section" n="9"/>Other ethical
                    indications are the accompanying peculiarities of each
                    individual character; for instance, “He was talking and walking on at
                    the same time,” which indicates effrontery and boorishness. Nor should
                    we speak as if from the intellect, after the manner of present-day orators; but
                    from moral purpose: “But I wished it, and I preferred it; and even if
                    I profited nothing, it is better.” The first statement indicates
                    prudence, the second virtue; for prudence consists in the pursuit of what is
                    useful, virtue in that of what is honorable. If anything of the kind seems
                    incredible, then the reason must be added; of this Sophocles gives an example,
                    where his Antigone says that she cared more for her brother than for her husband
                    or children; for the latter can be replaced after they are gone,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>but when father and mother are in the grave, no brother can ever be
                                born.
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Soph. Ant. 911-912"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Soph. Ant. 911-912</bibl>, where the
                                    mss. have <foreign lang="greek">κεκευθότοιν</foreign> instead
                                    of Aristotle's <foreign lang="greek">βεβηκότων</foreign>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    If you have no reason, you should at least say that you are aware that
                    what you assert is incredible, but that it is your nature; for no one believes
                    that a man ever does anything of his own free will except from motives of
                    self-interest.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Whereas this man makes his
                        temperament responsible for the strange things he does; he is built that way
                        and cannot help it.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="10"/>Further, the narrative should draw upon what is
                    emotional by the introduction of such of its accompaniments as are well known,
                    and of what is specially characteristic of either yourself or of the adversary:
                    “And he went off looking grimly at me”;
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1417b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>and as Aeschines
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Supposed to be Aeschines called Socraticus
                        from his intimate
                        friendship with
                        <persName>
                            <surname full="yes">Socrates</surname>
                        </persName>
                        . A philosopher and writer of speeches for the law
                        courts, he had a great reputation as an orator.
                    </note>
                    says of Cratylus,
                    that he hissed violently and violently shook his fists. Such details produce
                    persuasion because, being known to the hearer, they become tokens of what he
                    does not know. Numerous examples of this may be found in Homer:
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Thus she spoke, and the aged nurse covered her face with her
                                hands;
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 19.361"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Od. 19.361</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    for those who are beginning to weep lay hold on their eyes. And you
                    should at once introduce yourself and your adversary as being of a certain
                    character, that the hearers may regard you or him as such; but do not let it be
                    seen. That this is easy is perfectly clear
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign lang="greek">δεῖ</foreign>
                        （omitted by
                        others) = “one cannot help seeing.”
                    </note>
                    from
                    the example of messengers; we do not yet know what they are going to say, but
                    nevertheless we have an inkling of it.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="11"/>Again, the narrative should be introduced in
                    several places, sometimes not at all at the beginning. In deliberative oratory
                    narrative is very rare, because no one can narrate things to come; but if there
                    is narrative, it will be of things past, in order that, being reminded of them,
                    the hearers may take better counsel about the future. This may be done in a
                    spirit either of blame or of praise; but in that case the speaker does not
                    perform the function of the deliberative orator. If there is anything
                    incredible, you should immediately promise both to give a reason for it at once
                    and to submit it to the judgement of any whom the hearers approve;
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Omitting <foreign lang="greek">τε</foreign>.
                        The difficulty is <foreign lang="greek">διατάττειν</foreign>, which can
                        apparently only mean “arrange.” Jebb retains <foreign lang="greek">τε</foreign>, and reads
                        <foreign lang="greek">ὡς</foreign>
                        for <foreign lang="greek">οἷς</foreign>: “the speaker must make
                        himself responsible for the fact . . . and marshal his reasons in a way
                        acceptable to the hearers.” The old Latin translation <foreign lang="la">vadiare quibus volunt
                        </foreign> suggested to Roemer <foreign lang="greek">διαιτηταῖς</foreign>, “to the arbitrators
                        they
                        approve.”
                    </note>
                    as, for instance, Jocasta in the
                    <title>Oedipus</title>
                    of Carcinus<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">According
                        to Jebb, Jocasta tells the inquirer incredible things about her son, and
                        pledges her word for the facts. Cope says: “promises （to
                        do something or other to satisfy him).”
                    </note> is always
                    promising, when the man who is looking for her son makes inquiries<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>of her;
                    and similarly Haemon in Sophocles.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Soph. Ant. 683-723" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Soph. Ant.
                        683-723</bibl>. On this Cope remarks: “This last example must be
                        given up as hopeless; there is nothing in the extant play which could be
                        interpreted as required here.” According to Jebb, the
                        “incredibility” consists in the fact that Haemon,
                        although in love with Antigone, and strongly opposed to the sentence
                        pronounced upon her by his father Creon, still remains loyal to the latter.
                        Haemon explains the reason in lines 701-3, where he says that he prizes his
                        father's welfare more than anything else, for a father's good name and
                        prosperity is the greatest ornament for children, as is the son's for the
                        father.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="17"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>Proofs should
                    be demonstrative, and as the disputed points are four, the demonstration should
                    bear upon the particular point disputed; for instance, if the fact is disputed,
                    proof of this must be brought at the trial before anything else; or if it is
                    maintained that no injury has been done; or that the act was not so important as
                    asserted; or was just, then this must be proved, the three last questions being
                    matters of dispute just as the question of fact.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>But do not forget
                    that it is only in the case of a dispute as to this question
                    of fact that one of the two parties must necessarily
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Aristotle's argument is as follows. But it
                        must not be
                        forgotten that it is only in a dispute as to this question of fact that one
                        of the two parties must necessarily be a rogue. For ignorance is not the
                        cause （of there being a dispute about the fact, e.g. “you
                        hit me,” “no, I didn't,” where both know the
                        truth), as it might be in a dispute on what was right or wrong, so
                        that this is the topic on which you should spend some time （i.e.
                        because here you can prove or disprove that A is <foreign lang="greek">πονηρός</foreign>). The
                        passage is generally taken to mean
                        that when it is a question of fact it is universally true that one of the
                        disputants must be a rogue. Cope alone among editors makes any comment. In
                        his note he says: “all that is meant is that there is a certain
                        class of cases which fall under this issue, in which this topic may be
                        safely used.” For instance, A may on justifiable grounds charge B
                        with theft; B denies it, and he may be innocent, although the evidence is
                        strongly against him. In such a case, neither of the parties is necessarily
                        <foreign lang="greek">πονηρός</foreign>.
                    </note>
                    be a rogue; for
                    ignorance is not the cause, as it might be if a question of right or wrong were
                    the issue; so that in this case one should spend time on this topic, but not in
                    the others.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="3"/>In epideictic speeches, amplification is
                    employed, as a rule, to prove that things are honorable or useful; for the facts
                    must be taken on trust, since proofs of these are rarely given, and only if they
                    are incredible or the responsibility is attributed to another.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Or, reading <foreign lang="greek">
                        ἄλλως</foreign>, “if there is some other
                        reason.”
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="4"/>In deliberative oratory, it may be maintained
                    either that certain consequences will not happen, or that what the adversary
                    recommends will happen, but that it will be unjust, inexpedient, or not so
                    important as supposed. But one must also look to see whether he makes any false
                    statements as to things outside the issue; for these look like evidence that he
                    makes misstatements about the issue itself as well.
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1418a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="5"/>Examples are best suited to deliberative oratory
                    and enthymemes to forensic. The first is concerned with the future, so that its
                    examples must be derived from the past; the second with the question of the
                    existence or non-existence of facts, in which demonstrative and necessary proofs
                    are more in place; for the past involves a kind of necessity.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">It is irrevocable, and it is possible to
                        discuss it with some
                        degree of certainty, whereas the future is quite uncertain, and all that can
                        be done is to draw inferences from the past.
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="6"/>One should not introduce a series of enthymemes
                    continuously but mix them up; otherwise they destroy one another. For there is a
                    limit of quantity; thus,
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>Friend, since thou hast said as much as a wise man would say,
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 4.204"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Hom. Od.
                                    4.204</bibl>.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="7"/>where Homer does not say <foreign lang="greek">τοιαῦτα</foreign> （such
                    things as), but <foreign lang="greek">τόσα</foreign> （as many things as). Nor
                    should you try to find enthymemes about everything; otherwise you will be
                    imitating certain philosophers, who draw conclusions that are better known and
                    more plausible than the premises from which they are drawn.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">For this passage see 1.2.12-13. The meaning
                        is that it is
                        absurd to prove what every one knows already.
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="8"/>And whenever you wish to arouse emotion, do not
                    use an enthymeme, for it will either drive out the emotion or it will be
                    useless; for simultaneous movements drive each other out, the result being their
                    mutual destruction or weakening. Nor should you look for an enthymeme at the
                    time when you wish to give the speech an ethical character; for demonstration
                    involves neither moral character nor moral purpose.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="9"/>Moral maxims, on the other hand, should be used
                    in both narrative and proof; for they express moral character; for instance,
                    “I gave him the money and that although I knew that one ought not to
                    trust.” Or, to arouse emotion:<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>“I do
                    not regret it, although I have been wronged; his is the profit, mine the
                    right.”
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="10"/>Deliberative speaking is more difficult than
                    forensic, and naturally so, because it has to do with the future; whereas
                    forensic speaking has to do with the past, which is already known, even by
                    diviners, as Epimenides the Cretan said; for he used to divine, not the future,
                    but only things that were past but obscure.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The remark of Epimenides is by many editors
                        interpreted as a sarcasm upon
                        the fraternity of soothsayers, who pretended to be able to <emph>foretell
                            the future</emph>. But how is this to be got out of the Greek? The point
                        is perhaps something like: “it is easy enough to talk about the
                        past, for even soothsayers know it.” What Aristotle says here is
                        that Epimenides practised a different kind of divination, relating to the
                        obscure phenomena of the past. The following is an instance. After the
                        followers of Cylon, who tried to make himself tyrant of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                                                                           authname="perseus,Athens">
                            Athens
                        </placeName> （c. 632) had
                        been put to death by the Alcmaeonid archon Megacles, in violation of the
                        terms of surrender, a curse rested upon the city and it was devastated by a
                        pestilence. On the advice of the oracle, Epimenides was summoned from
                        <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, and by certain rites and
                        sacrifices purified the city and put a stop to the pestilence.
                    </note>
                    Further, the law is the subject in forensic speaking; and when one has a
                    starting-point, it is easier to find a demonstrative proof. Deliberative
                    speaking does not allow many opportunities for lingering—for instance,
                    attacks on the adversary, remarks about oneself, or attempts to arouse emotion.
                    In this branch of Rhetoric there is less room for these than in any other,
                    unless the speaker wanders from the subject. Therefore, when at a loss for
                    topics, one must do as the orators at <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">
                        Athens</placeName>, amongst them Isocrates, for even when deliberating, he
                    brings accusations against the Lacedaemonians, for instance, in the
                    <title>Panegyricus</title>,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Isoc. 4.110" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Isoc. 4.110-114</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    and against Chares in
                    the <title>Symmachikos</title> （On the Peace).
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Isoc. 8.27" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Isoc. 8.27</bibl>.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="11"/>Epideictic speeches should be varied with
                    laudatory episodes, after the manner of Isocrates, who is always bringing
                    somebody in. This is what Gorgias meant when he said that he was never at a loss
                    for something to say; for, if he is speaking of Peleus, he praises Achilles,
                    then Aeacus, then the god; similarly courage, which does this and that,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">He enumerates all the deeds that proceed from
                        courage. Another reading is <foreign lang="greek">ἢ τὰ καὶ τά, ποιεῖ
                            ὃ τοιόνδε ἐστίν</foreign>, i.e. when praising courage, and this or
                        that, he is employing a method of the kind mentioned.
                    </note>
                    or is of such a
                    kind.<milestone unit="section" n="12"/>If you have proofs, then, your language
                    must be both ethical and demonstrative; if you have no enthymemes, ethical only.
                    In fact, it is more fitting that a virtuous man
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1418b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>should show himself good than that his speech should be
                    painfully exact.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="13"/>Refutative enthymemes are more popular than
                    demonstrative, because, in all cases of refutation, it is clearer that a logical
                    conclusion has been reached; for opposites are more noticeable when placed in
                    juxtaposition.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">There is no difference in
                        form between the demonstrative and refutative enthymeme, but the latter
                        draws opposite conclusions; and opposites are always more striking when they
                        are brought together, and a parallel drawn between them. It is then easy to
                        see where the fallacy lies. Cf. 2.23.30: “Refutative enthymemes
                        are more effective （popular) than demonstrative, because
                        they bring opposites together in a small compass, which are more striking
                        （clearer) to the hearer from being put side by
                        side.”
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="14"/>The refutation of the opponent is not a
                    particular kind of proof; his arguments should be refuted partly by objection,
                    partly by counter-syllogism.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">In the
                        translation <foreign lang="greek">τῶν πίστεων</foreign> is taken with
                        <foreign lang="greek">ἔστι</foreign>: it is the business of, the
                        proper function of, proofs. Others take it with <foreign lang="greek">τὰ
                            μὲν . . . τὰ δέ</foreign>: some . . . other （of the
                        opponent's arguments).
                    </note>
                    In both deliberative and forensic
                    rhetoric he who speaks first should state his own proofs and afterwards meet the
                    arguments of the opponent, refuting or pulling them to pieces beforehand. But if
                    the opposition is varied,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">If the opponent's
                        arguments are numerous and strong, by reason of the varied nature of the
                        points dealt with.
                    </note> these arguments should be dealt with first, as
                    Callistratus did in the Messenian assembly; in fact, it was only after he had
                    first refuted what his opponents were likely to say that he put forward his own
                    proofs.<milestone unit="section" n="15"/>He who replies should first state the
                    arguments against the opponent's speech, refuting and answering it by
                    syllogisms, especially if his arguments have met with approval. For as the mind
                    is ill-disposed towards one against whom prejudices have been raised beforehand,
                    it is equally so towards a speech, if the adversary is thought to have spoken
                    well. One must therefore make room in the hearer's mind for the speech one
                    intends to make; and for this purpose you must destroy the impression made by
                    the adversary. Wherefore it is only after having combated all the arguments, or
                    the most important, or those which are plausible, or most easy to refute, that
                    you should substantiate your own case:
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>I will first defend the goddesses, for I [do not
                                think] that Hera . . .
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Eur. Tro. 969"
                                                                                             default="NO" valid="yes">
                                    Eur. Tro. 969-971</bibl>.
                                    Hecuba had advised Menelaus to put Helen to death; she defends
                                    herself at length, and is answered by Hecuba in a reply of which
                                    these words form part. Her argument is that none of the three
                                    goddesses who contended for the prize of beauty on Mt. Ida would
                                    have been such fools as to allow <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
                                                                                authname="perseus,Argos">Argos
                                    </placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens
                                    </placeName> to become subject to <placeName key="tgn,7002329"
                                                                                 authname="tgn,7002329">Troy
                                    </placeName> as the result of the
                                    contest, which was merely a prank.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    in this passage the poet has first seized upon the weakest argument.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="16"/>So much concerning proofs. In regard to moral
                    character, since sometimes, in speaking of ourselves, we render ourselves liable
                    to envy, to the charge of prolixity, or contradiction, or, when speaking of
                    another, we may be accused of abuse or boorishness, we must make another speak
                    in our place, as Isocrates does in the
                    <title>Philippus</title>
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Isoc. 5.4" default="NO" valid="yes">
                        Isoc. 5.4-7</bibl>.
                        Isocrates says that <emph>his friends</emph> thought very highly of one of
                        his addresses, as likely to bring peace.
                    </note>
                    and in the
                    <title>Antidosis</title>.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Isoc. 15.132" default="NO"
                                                                                 valid="yes">Isoc. 15.132-139</bibl>
                        , <bibl n="Isoc. 15.141" default="NO" valid="yes">Isoc. 15.141-149</bibl>. Here again Isocrates
                        puts compliments on his
                        composition into the mouth of an imaginary friend.
                    </note>
                    Archilochus uses
                    the same device in censure; for in his iambics he introduces the father speaking
                    as follows of his daughter:
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="troch" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>There is nothing beyond expectation, nothing that can be sworn
                                impossible,
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Archilochus
                                    （c. 650) of <placeName key="tgn,7011023" authname="tgn,7011023">Paros</placeName> was
                                    engaged to Neobule, the daughter of
                                    Lycambes. Her father broke off the engagement, whereupon
                                    Archilochus pursued father and daughter with furious and
                                    scurrilous abuse. It is here said that, instead of attacking the
                                    daughter directly, he represented her as being attacked by her
                                    father. The meaning of
                                    <foreign lang="greek">ἄελπτον</foreign>
                                    is not clear. It may be a general statement: the unexpected
                                    often happens; or, there is nothing so bad that you may not
                                    expect it. B. St. Hilaire translates: “There is
                                    nothing that money cannot procure,” meaning that the
                                    father was prepared to sell his daughter （Frag.
                                    74).
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    and the carpenter Charon in the iambic verse beginning
                    <quote>
                        <lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                            <l>I [care not for the wealth] of Gyges;
                                <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The line ends: <foreign
                                        lang="greek">τοῦ πολυχρύσου μέλει</foreign>. Archilochus
                                    represents Charon the carpenter as expressing his own
                                    disapproval of the desire for wealth and of the envy caused by
                                    others possessing it.
                                </note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote>
                    Sophocles, also,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Here again, Haemon
                        similarly puts his own feeling as to Creon's cruel treatment of Antigone
                        into the mouth of the people of the city, and refers to popular
                        rumor.
                    </note> introduces Haemon, when defending Antigone against his father, as
                    if quoting the opinion of others.<milestone unit="section" n="17"/>One should
                    also sometimes change enthymemes into moral maxims; for instance,
                    “Sensible men should become reconciled when they are prosperous; for
                    in this manner they will obtain the greatest advantages,” which is
                    equivalent to the enthymeme “If men should become reconciled whenever
                    it is most useful and advantageous, they should be reconciled in a time of
                    prosperity.”
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="18"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>In regard to
                    interrogation, its employment is especially opportune,
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1419a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>when the opponent has already stated the opposite,
                    so that the addition of a question makes the result an absurdity
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The words <foreign lang="greek">ὅταν . . .
                        ᾖ
                    </foreign> have been variously translated: （1)
                        when one of the two alternatives has already been stated;
                        （2) when the opponent has stated what is different from
                        the fact; （3) when the opponent has already conceded so
                        much, “made one admission”
                        （Jebb).
                    </note>
                    ; as, for instance, when Pericles interrogated
                    Lampon about initiation into the sacred rites of the savior goddess. On Lampon
                    replying that it was not possible for one who was not initiated to be told about
                    them, Pericles asked him if he himself was acquainted with the rites, and when
                    he said yes, Pericles further asked, “How can that be, seeing that you
                    are uninitiated?”<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>Again,
                    interrogation should be employed when one of the two propositions is evident,
                    and it is obvious that the opponent will admit the other if you ask him. But the
                    interrogator, having obtained the second premise by putting a question, should
                    not make an additional question of what is evident, but should state the
                    conclusion. For instance,
                    <persName>
                        <surname full="yes">Socrates</surname>
                    </persName>
                    , when accused by Meletus of not believing in
                    the gods, asked
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Reading <foreign lang="greek">ἤρετο</foreign>.
                    </note>
                    whether he did not say that there was a
                    divine something; and when Meletus said yes,
                    <persName>
                        <surname full="yes">Socrates</surname>
                    </persName>
                    went on to ask if divine
                    beings were not either children of the gods or something godlike. When Meletus
                    again said yes,
                    <persName>
                        <surname full="yes">Socrates</surname>
                    </persName>
                    rejoined,<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>“Is there a man, then, who can admit that the children of
                    the gods
                    exist without at the same time admitting that the gods exist?”
                    Thirdly, when it is intended to show that the opponent either contradicts
                    himself or puts forward a paradox.<milestone unit="section" n="4"/>Further,
                    when the opponent can do nothing else but answer the question by a sophistical
                    solution; for if he answers, “Partly yes, and partly no,”
                    “Some are, but some are not,” “In one sense it is
                    so, in another not,” the hearers cry out against him as being in a
                    difficulty.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">For the first of the quibbles
                        Sandys refers to <bibl n="Aristoph. Ach. 396" default="NO" valid="yes">Aristoph. Ach. 396</bibl>,
                        where Cephisophon, being asked if Euripides was indoors, replies,
                        “Yes and no, if you understand me”; and he gives the
                        explanation, his mind is outside, collecting scraps of poetry, while he
                        himself is upstairs （ <foreign lang="greek">ἀναβάδην</foreign>,
                        unless it means “with his legs up”) composing a
                        tragedy. The reference in the second instance is to the adversary being
                        reduced to such a position that he cannot answer without having recourse to
                        sophistical divisions and distinctions, which seem to imply uncertainty.
                        Aristotle himself is fond of such “cautiously limited
                        judgements” （Gomperz). The translation is that
                        of the reading <foreign lang="greek">ἀποροῦντος</foreign>, a conjecture of
                        Spengel's. The audience will be ready to express its disapproval of his
                        shuffling answers, which are evidence of his perplexity. The ordinary
                        reading <foreign lang="greek">ἀποροῦντες</foreign> attributes the
                        “perplexity” to the hearers. Or, “the hearers,
                        thinking he is puzzled, <emph>applaud us</emph> [the
                        interrogator]” （Jebb).
                    </note>
                    In other
                    cases interrogation should not be attempted; for if the adversary raises an
                    objection, the interrogator seems to be defeated; for it is impossible to ask a
                    number of questions, owing to the hearer's weakness. Wherefore also we should
                    compress our enthymemes as much as possible.
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="5"/>Ambiguous questions should be answered by
                    defining them by a regular explanation, and not too concisely; those that appear
                    likely to make us contradict ourselves should be solved at once in the answer,
                    before the adversary has time to ask the next question or to draw a conclusion;
                    for it is not difficult to see the drift of his argument. Both this, however,
                    and the means of answering will be sufficiently clear from the
                    <title>Topics</title>.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Aristot. Top. 8.4" default="NO">
                        Aristot. Top. 8.4</bibl>.
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="6"/>If a conclusion is put in the form of a
                    question, we should state the reason for our answer. For instance,
                    Sophocles<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Cp. 1.14.3.</note> being asked
                    by Pisander whether he, like the rest of the Committee of Ten, had approved the
                    setting up of the Four Hundred, he admitted it. “What then?”
                    asked Pisander, “did not this appear to you to be a wicked
                    thing?” Sophocles admitted it. “So then you did what was
                    wicked?” “Yes, for there was nothing better to be
                    done.” The Lacedaemonian, who was called to account for his ephoralty,
                    being asked if he did not think that the rest of his colleagues had been justly
                    put to death, answered yes. “But did not you pass the same measures as
                    they did?” “Yes.” “Would not you, then,
                    also be justly put to death?” “No; for my colleagues did
                    this for money; I did not, but acted according to my conscience.” For
                    this reason we should not ask any further questions after drawing the
                    conclusion,
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1419b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>nor put the
                    conclusion itself as a question, unless the balance of truth is unmistakably in
                    our favor.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="7"/>As for jests, since they may sometimes be useful
                    in debates, the advice of Gorgias was good—to confound the opponents'
                    earnest with jest and their jest with earnest. We have stated in the
                    <title>Poetics</title>
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The chapters are
                        lost （cp. 1.11.29).
                    </note>
                    how many kinds of jests there
                    are, some of them becoming a gentleman, others not. You should therefore choose
                    the kind that suits you. Irony is more gentlemanly than buffoonery; for the
                    first is employed on one's own account, the second on that of another.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="19"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>The epilogue
                    is composed of four parts: to dispose the hearer favorably towards oneself and
                    unfavorably towards the adversary; to amplify and depreciate; to excite the
                    emotions of the hearer; to recapitulate. For after you have proved that you are
                    truthful and that the adversary is false, the natural order of things is to
                    praise ourselves, blame him, and put the finishing touches.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes"
                                                                                     place="unspecified">Or, “mould the
                    hearers to one's will”
                    （L. and S.).
                </note> One of two things should be aimed at,
                    to show that you are either relatively or absolutely good and the adversary
                    either relatively or absolutely bad. The topics which serve to represent men as
                    good or bad have already been stated.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Book
                        1.9.
                    </note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>After this,<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>when the
                    proof has once been established, the natural thing is to amplify or depreciate;
                    for it is necessary that the facts should be admitted, if it is intended to deal
                    with the question of degree; just as the growth of the body is due to things
                    previously existing. The topics of amplification and depreciation have been
                    previously set forth.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Book 2.19.</note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>Next, when the nature and importance of the
                    facts are clear, one should rouse the hearer to certain emotions—pity,
                    indignation, anger, hate, jealousy, emulation, and quarrelsomeness. The topics
                    of these also have been previously stated,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Book 2.1-11.</note>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="4"/>so that all that remains is to recapitulate
                    what has been said. This may appropriately be done at this stage in the way
                    certain rhetoricians wrongly recommend for the exordium, when they advise
                    frequent repetition of the points, so that they may be easily learnt. In the
                    exordium we should state the subject, in order that the question to be decided
                    may not escape notice, but in the epilogue we should give a summary statement of
                    the proofs.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="5"/>We should begin by saying that we have kept our
                    promise, and then state what we have said and why. Our case may also be closely
                    compared with our opponent's; and we may either compare what both of us have
                    said on the same point, or without direct comparison: “My opponent
                    said so-and-so, and I said so-and-so on this point
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1420a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>and for these reasons.” Or ironically, as
                    for instance, “He said this and I answered that; what would he have
                    done, if he had proved this, and not simply that?” Or by
                    interrogation: “What is there that has not been proved?” or,
                    “What has my opponent proved?” We may, therefore, either sum
                    up by comparison, or in the natural order of the statements, just as they were
                    made, our own first, and then again, separately, if we so desire, what has been
                    said by our opponent.<milestone unit="section" n="6"/>To the conclusion of the
                    speech
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Reading <foreign lang="greek">
                        τελευτῇ</foreign>, a conjecture of Victorius. With <foreign lang="greek">τελευτή</foreign>, the
                        sense will be: “as a
                        conclusion, the asyndectic style is appropriate.”
                    </note>
                    the most
                    appropriate style is that which has no connecting particles, in order that it
                    may be a peroration, but not an oration: “I have spoken; you have
                    heard; you know the facts; now give your decision.”
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">It is generally supposed that this example of
                        a suitable
                        peroration is an echo of the conclusion of the speech of Lysias
                        <title>Against Eratosthenes</title>.
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>