<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <text lang="en">
        <body>
            <div1 n="1" type="book" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="chapter" n="3"/>
                    <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>The kinds of
                    Rhetoric are three in number, corresponding to the three kinds of hearers. For
                    every speech is composed of three parts: the speaker,
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1358b"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>the subject of which he treats, and the person to
                    whom it is addressed, I mean the hearer, to whom the end or object of the speech
                    refers.<milestone unit="section" n="2"/>Now the hearer must necessarily be
                    either a mere spectator or a judge, and a judge either of things past or of
                    things to come.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">All three kinds of hearers are
                        regarded as judges （the mere spectator as a
                        “critic”）, although strictly <foreign lang="greek">κριτής</foreign> should be limited to the law
                        courts.
                    </note>
                    For instance, a member of the general assembly is a judge of
                    things to come; the dicast, of things past; the mere spectator, of the ability
                    of the speaker.<milestone unit="section" n="3"/>Therefore there are necessarily
                    three kinds of rhetorical speeches, deliberative, forensic, and epideictic.
                </p>
                <p>The deliberative kind is either hortatory or dissuasive; for both those who give
                    advice in private and those who speak in the assembly invariably either exhort
                    or dissuade. The forensic kind is either accusatory or defensive; for litigants
                    must necessarily either accuse or defend. The epideictic kind has for its
                    subject praise or blame.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="4"/>Further, to each of these a special time is
                    appropriate: to the deliberative the future,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">
                        In 1.6.I and 8.7 the present is also mentioned as a time appropriate to
                        deliberative Rhetoric.
                    </note> for the speaker, whether he exhorts or
                    dissuades, always advises about things to come; to the forensic the past, for it
                    is always in reference to things done that one party accuses and the other
                    defends; to the epideictic most appropriately the present, for it is the
                    existing condition of things that all those who praise or blame have in view. It
                    is not uncommon, however, for epideictic speakers to avail themselves of other
                    times, of the past<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>by way of recalling it, or of the
                    future by way of anticipating it.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="5"/>Each of the three kinds has a different special
                    end, and as there are three kinds of Rhetoric, so there are three special ends.
                    The end of the deliberative speaker Is the expedient or harmful; for he who
                    exhorts recommends a course of action as better, and he who dissuades advises
                    against it as worse; all other considerations, such as justice and injustice,
                    honor and disgrace, are included as accessory in reference to this. The end of
                    the forensic speaker is the just or the unjust; in this case also all other
                    considerations are included as accessory. The end of those who praise or blame
                    is the honorable and disgraceful; and they also refer all other considerations
                    to these.<milestone unit="section" n="6"/>A sign that what I have stated is the
                    end which each has in view is the fact that sometimes the speakers will not
                    dispute about the other points. For example, a man on trial does not always deny
                    that an act has been committed or damage inflicted by him, but he will never
                    admit that the act is unjust; for otherwise a trial would be unnecessary.
                    Similarly, the deliberative orator, although he often sacrifices everything
                    else, will never admit that he is recommending what is inexpedient or is
                    dissuading from what is useful; but often he is quite indifferent about showing
                    that the enslavement of neighboring peoples, even if they have done no harm, is
                    not an act of injustice.
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The omission of
                        <foreign lang="greek">οὐκ</foreign>
                        before <foreign lang="greek">ἄδικον</foreign> has been suggested. The sense would then be:
                        “As to the injustice of enslaving . . . he is quite
                        indifferent.” There is no doubt a reference to the cruel treatment
                        by <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> of the
                        inhabitants of
                        the island of <placeName key="tgn,7010922" authname="tgn,7010922">Melos</placeName> （<date
                                value="-416" authname="-416">416
                        </date> B.C.） for its loyalty to the Spartans
                        during the Peloponnesian war （<bibl n="Thuc. 5.84-116" default="NO" valid="yes">Thuc.
                            5.84-116</bibl>）. The Athenian envoys declined to discuss the
                        question of right or wrong, which they said was only possible between equal
                        powers, and asserted that <emph>expediency</emph> was the only thing that
                        had to be considered. The question of justice or injustice （in the
                        Melian case entirely disregarded）, even when taken into account,
                        was merely accessory and intended to serve as a specious justification for
                        the policy of might.
                    </note>
                    Similarly, those who praise or blame do not
                    consider
                    <pb ed="Bekker" n="1359a"/>
                    <lb ed="Bekker" n="1"/>whether a man has
                    done what is expedient or harmful, but frequently make it a matter for praise
                    that, disregarding his own interest, he performed some deed of honor. For
                    example, they praise Achilles because he went to the aid of his comrade
                    Patroclus,
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">To protect his body and avenge
                        his death （<bibl n="Hom. Il. 18" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il.
                            18</bibl>.）.
                    </note>
                    knowing that he was fated to die, although he might
                    have lived. To him such a death was more honorable, although life was more
                    expedient.
                </p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" n="7"/>From what has been said it is evident that the
                    orator must first have in readiness the propositions on these three
                    subjects.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The expedient, the just, the
                        honorable, and their contraries.
                    </note> Now, necessary signs, probabilities,
                    and signs are the propositions of the rhetorician; for the syllogism
                    universally
                    <note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><foreign lang="greek">ὅλως</foreign>: or,
                        reading <foreign lang="greek">ὅλος</foreign>,
                        “the syllogism as a whole.”
                    </note>
                    consists of
                    propositions, and the enthymeme is a syllogism composed of the propositions
                    above mentioned.<milestone unit="section" n="8"/>Again, since what is
                    impossible can neither have been done nor will be done, but only what is
                    possible, and since what has not taken place nor will take place can neither
                    have been done nor will be done, it is necessary for each of the three kinds of
                    orators to have in readiness propositions dealing with the possible and the
                    impossible, and as to whether anything has taken place or will take place, or
                    not.<milestone unit="section" n="9"/>Further, since all, whether they praise or
                    blame, exhort or dissuade, accuse or defend, not only endeavor to prove what we
                    have stated, but also that the same things,<lb ed="Bekker" n="20"/>whether good
                    or bad, honorable or disgraceful, just or unjust, are great or small, either in
                    themselves or when compared with each other, it is clear that it will be
                    necessary for the orator to be ready with propositions dealing with greatness
                    and smallness and the greater and the less, both universally and in particular;
                    for instance, which is the greater or less good, or act of injustice or justice;
                    and similarly with regard to all other subjects. We have now stated the topics
                    concerning which the orator must provide himself with propositions; after this,
                    we must distinguish between each of them individually, that is, what the three
                    kinds of Rhetoric, deliberative, epideictic, and forensic, are concerned with.
                </p>
                <p/>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>