<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text lang="en"><body><div1 n="1" type="book" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p><milestone unit="chapter" n="15" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" />Following on
					what we have just spoken of, we have now briefly to run over what are called the
					inartificial proofs, for these properly belong to forensic oratory. <milestone unit="section" n="2" />These proofs are five in number: laws, witnesses,
					contracts, torture, oaths. <milestone unit="section" n="3" />Let us first then
					speak of the laws, and state what use should be made of them when exhorting or
					dissuading,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Although the use of
						inartificial proofs is almost entirely confined to forensic oratory, they
						<emph>may</emph> be used in deliberative oratory.</note> accusing or
					defending. <milestone unit="section" n="4" />For it is evident that, if the
					written law is counter to our case, we must have recourse to the general law and
					equity, as more in accordance with justice; <milestone unit="section" n="5" />and
					we must argue that, when the dicast takes an oath to decide to the best of his
					judgement, he means that he will not abide rigorously by the written laws;
					<milestone unit="section" n="6" />that equity is ever constant and never
					changes, even as the general law, which is based on nature, whereas the written
					laws often vary （this is why Antigone in Sophocles justifies herself
					for having buried Polynices contrary to the law of Creon, but not contrary to
					the unwritten law: <pb ed="Bekker" n="1375b" /><lb ed="Bekker" n="1" /><quote>
						<lg type="iamb" org="uniform" sample="complete">
							<l>For this law is not of now or yesterday, but is eternal . . . this I
								was not likely [to infringe through fear of the
								pride] of any man）;<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The first line is quoted 1.13.2. The second
									differs somewhat from <bibl n="Soph. Ant. 458" default="NO" valid="yes">Soph. Ant.
										458</bibl>, where the passage runs, <foreign lang="greek">τούτων ἐγὼ οὐκ ἔμελλον, ἀνδρὸς οὐδινὸς φρόνημα
											δείσασ᾽, ἐν θεοῖσι τὴν δίκην δώσειν</foreign>
									（“I was not likely, through fear of the pride
									of any man, to incur the penalty for violating these statutes at
									the bar of heaven”）.</note></l>
						</lg>
					</quote>
					<milestone unit="section" n="7" />and further, that justice is real and
					expedient, but not that which only appears just; nor the written law either,
					because it does not do the work of the law<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Which is the administration of real justice, not that which appears to the
						legislator to be such and is embodied in legal enactments.</note>; that the
					judge is like an assayer of silver, whose duty is to distinguish spurious from
					genuine justice; <milestone unit="section" n="8" />that it is the part of a
					better man to make use of and abide by the unwritten rather than the written
					law.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Cp.14.7 above.</note>
					<milestone unit="section" n="9" />Again, it is necessary to see whether the law
					is contradictory to another approved law or to itself; for instance, one law
					enacts that all contracts should be binding, while another forbids making
					contracts contrary to the law. <milestone unit="section" n="10" />If the meaning
					of the law is equivocal, we must turn it about, and see in which way it is to be
					interpreted so as to suit the application of justice or expediency, and have
					recourse to that. <milestone unit="section" n="11" />If the conditions which led
					to the enactment of the law are now obsolete, while the law itself remains, one
					must endeavor to make this clear and to combat the law by this argument.
					<milestone unit="section" n="12" />But if the written law favors our case, we
					must say that the oath of the dicast “to decide to the best of his
					judgement” does not justify him in deciding contrary to the law, but
					is only intended to relieve him from the charge of perjury, if he is ignorant of
					the meaning of the law; that no one chooses that which is good absolutely, but
					that which is good for himself;<lb ed="Bekker" n="20" />that there is no
					difference between not using the laws and their not being enacted; that in the
					other arts there is no advantage in trying to be wiser than the physician, for
					an error on his part does not do so much harm as the habit of disobeying the
					authority; that to seek to be wiser than the laws is just what is forbidden in
					the most approved laws. Thus much for the laws.</p>
				<p><milestone unit="section" n="13" />Witnesses are of two kinds, ancient and recent;
					of the latter some share the risk of the trial, others are outside it. By
					ancient I mean the poets and men of repute whose judgements are known to all;
					for instance, the Athenians, in the matter of <placeName key="tgn,7002340" authname="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>, appealed to Homer<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><foreign lang="greek">Αἴας δ᾽ ἐκ Σαλαμῖνος ἄγεν δυοκαίδεκα
								νῆας, στῆσε δ᾽ ἄγων ἵν᾽ Α᾿θηναίων ἵσταντο φάλαγγες</foreign>,
							<bibl n="Hom. Il. 2.557-558" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.557-558</bibl>. The
							Lacedaemonians, acting as arbitrators between <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and Megara, who were fighting
							for the possession of <placeName key="tgn,7002340" authname="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>,
							decided in favor of <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> on
							the strength of the two lines in the <title>Iliad</title>, which were taken
							to show that <placeName key="tgn,7002340" authname="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName> belonged to
							<placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. It was reported that
							the second line was the invention of Solon.</note> as a witness, and
					recently the inhabitants of <placeName key="perseus,Tenedos" authname="perseus,Tenedos">Tenedos</placeName>
					to Periander of <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName><note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">It is not known to what this refers.</note>
					against the Sigeans. Cleophon also made use of the elegiacs of Solon against
					Critias, to prove that his family had long been notorious for licentiousness,
					otherwise Solon would never have written: <quote>
						<lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
							<l>Bid me the fair-haired Critias listen to his father.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">（Frag. 22,
								<title>P.L.G.</title> 2, where the line runs, <foreign lang="greek">εἰπέμεναι Κριτίᾳ ξανθότριχι πατρὸς
									ἀκούειν</foreign>）. The Critias attacked by
								Cleophon is the well-known oligarch and grandson of the first.
								Cleophon argued from the phrase “bid him listen to his
								father” that his ancestor was a disobedient son and a
								degenerate. In reality, Solon had a high opinion of the family,
								and probably meant to praise the father.</note></l>
						</lg>
					</quote>
					<milestone unit="section" n="14" />One should appeal to such witnesses for the
					past, <pb ed="Bekker" n="1376a" /><lb ed="Bekker" n="1" />but also to interpreters
					of oracles for the future; thus, for instance, Themistocles interpreted the
					wooden wall to mean that they must fight at sea.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hdt. 7.141" default="NO" valid="yes">Hdt. 7.141</bibl>.</note> Further,
					proverbs, as stated,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">They have not been
						mentioned before. Spengel would therefore omit <foreign lang="greek">εἴρηται</foreign>, and remove the commas: “proverbs are, as
						it were, evidence.”</note> are evidence; for instance, if one man
					advises another not to make a friend of an old man, he can appeal to the
					proverb, <quote>Never do good to an old man.</quote> And if he advises another
					to kill the children, after having killed the fathers, he can say, <quote>
						<lg type="dact" org="uniform" sample="complete">
							<l>Foolish is he who, having killed the father, suffers the children to
								live.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">From the
									<title>Cypria</title> of Stasinus, of the “epic
									cycle.”</note></l>
						</lg>
					</quote></p>
				<p><milestone unit="section" n="15" />By recent witnesses I mean all well-known
					persons who have given a decision on any point, for their decisions are useful
					to those who are arguing about similar cases. Thus for instance, Eubulus,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Opponent of Demosthenes. Chares was an Athenian
						commander, both naval and military. Nothing is known of Archibius. Plato is
						probably the comic poet.</note> when attacking Chares in the law courts,
					made use of what Plato said against Archibius, namely, “that the open
					confession of wickedness had increased in the city.” <milestone unit="section" n="16" />And those who share the risk of the trial, if they
					are thought to be perjurers. Such witnesses only serve to establish whether an
					act has taken place or not, whether it is or is not the case; but if it is a
					question of the quality of the act, for instance, whether it is just or unjust,
					expedient or inexpedient, <milestone unit="section" n="17" />they are not
					competent witnesses; but witnesses from a distance<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Or, “witnesses wholly unconnected with the
						case.”</note> are very trustworthy even in regard to this. But
					ancient witnesses are the most trustworthy of all, for they cannot be corrupted.
					In regard to the confirmation of evidence, when a man has no witnesses, he can
					say that the decision should be given in accordance with probabilities, and that
					this is the meaning of the oath “according to the best of one's
					judgement”; that probabilities cannot<lb ed="Bekker" n="20" />be bribed
					to deceive, and that they cannot be convicted of bearing false witness. But if a
					man has witnesses and his adversary has none, he can say that probabilities
					incur no responsibility, and that there would have been no need of evidence, if
					an investigation according to the arguments were sufficient. <milestone unit="section" n="18" />Evidence partly concerns ourselves, partly our
					adversary, as to the fact itself or moral character; so that it is evident that
					one never need lack useful evidence. For, if we have no evidence as to the fact
					itself, neither in confirmation of our own case nor against our opponent, it
					will always be possible to obtain some evidence as to character that will
					establish either our own respectability or the worthlessness of our opponent.
					<milestone unit="section" n="19" />As for all the other questions relative to
					a witness, whether he is a friend, an enemy, or neutral, of good or bad or
					middling reputation, and for all other differences of this kind, we must have
					recourse to the same topics as those from which we derive our enthymemes.</p>
				<p><milestone unit="section" n="20" />As for contracts, argument may be used to the
					extent of magnifying or minimizing their importance, of proving that they do or
					do not deserve credit. <pb ed="Bekker" n="1376b" /><lb ed="Bekker" n="1" />If we
					have them on our side, we must try to prove them worthy of credit and
					authoritative; but if they are on the side of our opponent, we must do the
					opposite. <milestone unit="section" n="21" />In view of rendering them worthy or
					unworthy of credit, the method of procedure is exactly the same as in the case
					of witnesses; for contracts are trustworthy according to the character of their
					signatories or depositaries. When the existence of the contract is admitted, if
					it is in our favor, we must strengthen it by asserting that the contract is a
					law, special and partial; and it is not the contracts that make the law
					authoritative, but it is the laws that give force to legal contracts. And in a
					general sense the law itself is a kind of contract, so that whoever disobeys or
					subverts a contract, subverts the laws. <milestone unit="section" n="22" />Further, most ordinary and all voluntary transactions are carried out
					according to contract; so that if you destroy the authority of contracts, the
					mutual intercourse of men is destroyed. All other arguments suitable to the
					occasion are easy to see. <milestone unit="section" n="23" />But if the contract
					is against us and in favor of our opponents, in the first place those arguments
					are suitable which we should oppose to the law if it were against us; that it
					would be strange if, while we consider ourselves entitled to refuse to obey
					ill-made laws, whose authors have erred, we should be obliged to consider
					ourselves always bound by contracts.<milestone unit="section" n="24" />Or, that
					the judge<lb ed="Bekker" n="20" />is the dispenser of justice; so that it is not
					the contents of the contract that he has to consider, but what is juster.
					<milestone unit="section" n="25" />Further, that one cannot alter justice
					either by fraud or compulsion, for it is based upon nature, whereas contracts
					may be entered into under both conditions. In addition to this, we must examine
					whether the contract is contrary to any written law of our own or foreign
					countries, or to any general law, or to other previous or subsequent contracts.
					For either the latter are valid and the former not, or the former are right and
					the latter fraudulent; we may put it in whichever way it seems fit. We must also
					consider the question of expediency—whether the contract is in any way
					opposed to the interest of the judges. There are a number of other arguments of
					the same kind, which are equally easy to discern.</p>
				<p><milestone unit="section" n="26" />Torture is a kind of evidence, which appears
					trustworthy, because a sort of compulsion is attached to it. Nor is it difficult
					to see what may be said concerning it, and by what arguments, if it is in our
					favor, we can exaggerate its importance by asserting that it is the only true
					kind of evidence; <pb ed="Bekker" n="1377a" /><lb ed="Bekker" n="1" />but if it is
					against us and in favor of our opponent, we can destroy its value by telling the
					truth about all kinds of torture generally; for those under compulsion are as
					likely to give false evidence as true, some being ready to endure everything
					rather than tell the truth, while others are equally ready to make false charges
					against others, in the hope of being sooner released from torture. It is also
					necessary to be able to quote actual examples of the kind with which the judges
					are acquainted. It may also be said that evidence given under torture is not
					true; for many thick-witted and thick-skinned persons, and those who are
					stout-hearted heroically hold out under sufferings, while the cowardly and
					cautious, before they see the sufferings before them, are bold enough; wherefore
					evidence from torture may be considered utterly untrustworthy.</p>
				<p><milestone unit="section" n="27" />As to oaths<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">In Attic legal procedure, the challenge （ <foreign lang="greek">πρόκλησις</foreign>） to take an oath on the question at issue
					was one method of deciding it. One party offered the other something to
					swear by （ <foreign lang="greek">δίδωσι
						ὅρκον</foreign>）, this being the real meaning of <foreign lang="greek">ὅρκος</foreign>, and the other party either accepted
					（ <foreign lang="greek">λαμβάνει, δέχεται</foreign>） it
					or refused it. Both parties, of their own accord, might propose to take the
					oath.</note> four divisions may be made; for either we tender an oath and
					accept it, or we do neither, or one without the other, and in the last case we
					either tender but do not accept, or accept but do not tender. Besides this, one
					may consider whether the oath has already been taken by us or by the other
					party. <milestone unit="section" n="28" />If you do not tender the oath to the
					adversary, it is because men readily perjure themselves, and because, after he
					has taken the oath, he will refuse to repay the money, while, if he does not
					take the oath, you think that the dicasts will condemn him; and also because the
					risk incurred in leaving the decision to the dicasts is preferable, for you have
					confidence in them, but not in your adversary.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">There are three reasons for not tendering the oath: （1）
						men are always ready to perjure themselves, if they are likely to benefit by
						doing so; （2） if your adversary takes the oath, he will
						decline to pay, trusting that he will be acquitted, whereas, if he is not on
						his oath, he will probably be condemned; （3） there is less
						risk in leaving the decision to the dicasts, who can be trusted.</note>
					<milestone unit="section" n="29" />If you refuse to take the oath yourself, you
					may argue that the oath is only taken with a view to money; that, if you had
					been a scoundrel, you would have taken it at once, for it is better to be a
					scoundrel for something than for nothing; that, if you take it, you will win
					your case, if not, you will probably lose it; consequently, your refusal to take
					it is due to moral excellence, not to fear of committing perjury. And the
					apophthegm of Xenophanes<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Born at <placeName key="perseus,Colophon" authname="perseus,Colophon">Colophon</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,7002294" authname="tgn,7002294">Asia Minor</placeName>, he migrated to <placeName key="perseus,Elea" authname="perseus,Elea">Elea</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, where he founded the Eleatic school of
						philosophy.</note> is apposite— that “it is unfair<lb ed="Bekker" n="20" />for an impious man to challenge a pious one,”
					for it is the same as a strong man challenging a weak one to hit or be hit.
					<milestone unit="section" n="30" />If you accept the oath, you may say that
					you have confidence in yourself, but not in your opponent, and, reversing the
					apophthegm of Xenophanes, that the only fair way is that the impious man should
					tender the oath and the pious man take it; and that it would be monstrous to
					refuse to take the oath yourself, while demanding that the judges should take it
					before giving their verdict. <milestone unit="section" n="31" />But if you tender
					the oath, you may say that it is an act of piety to be willing to leave the
					matter to the gods; that your opponent has no need to look for other judges, for
					you allow him to make the decision himself; <milestone unit="section" n="32" />and that it would be ridiculous that he should be unwilling to take an oath in
					cases where he demands that the dicasts should take one.</p>
				<p>Now, since we have shown how we must deal with each case individually, it is
					clear how we must deal with them when taken two and two; for instance, if we
					wish to take the oath but not to tender it, to tender it but not to take it, to
					accept and tender it, or to do neither the one nor the other. <pb ed="Bekker" n="1377b" /><lb ed="Bekker" n="1" />For such cases, and similarly the
					arguments, must be a combination of those already mentioned. And if we have
					already taken an oath which contradicts the present one, we may argue that it is
					not perjury; for whereas wrongdoing is voluntary, and perjury is wrongdoing,
					what is done in error or under compulsion is involuntary. <milestone unit="section" n="33" />Here we must draw the conclusion that perjury
					consists in the intention, not in what is said.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The defence in such cases is: （1） that the
						previous oath was taken as a result of fraud or compulsion;
						（2） that you did not mean what you said.</note> But if the
					opponent has taken such an oath, we may say that one who does not abide by what
					be has sworn subverts everything, for this is the reason why the dicasts take an
					oath before applying the laws; and [we may make this appeal]:
					“They demand that you abide by your oath as judges, while they
					themselves do not abide by theirs.” Further, we should employ all
					means of amplification. Let this suffice for the inartificial proofs.</p>
			</div1></body></text></TEI.2>