<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text lang="en"><body><div1 n="1" type="book" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p><milestone unit="chapter" n="14" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" />Wrong acts are
					greater in proportion to the injustice from which they spring. For this reason
					the most trifling are sometimes the greatest, as in the charge brought by
					Callistratus<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">1.7.13. Callistratus and
						Melanopus were rival orators. Nothing is known of this particular
						charge.</note> against Melanopus that he had fraudulently kept back three
					consecrated half-obols from the temple-builders<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The magistrates who superintended the building and repairing
						operations.</note>; whereas, in the case of just actions, it is quite the
					contrary. The reason is that the greater potentially inheres in the less; for he
					who has stolen three consecrated half-obols will commit any wrong whatever.
					Wrong acts are judged greater sometimes in this way, sometimes by the extent of
					the injury done. <milestone unit="section" n="2" />A wrong act is greater when
					there is no adequate punishment for it, but all are insufficient; when there is
					no remedy, because it is difficult if not impossible to repair it;<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Understanding <foreign lang="greek">ἰᾶσθαι</foreign>. Or “to punish adequately,”
						supplying <foreign lang="greek">οὗ μὴ ἴση τιμωρία</foreign>.</note>
					and when the person injured cannot obtain legal satisfaction, since it is
					irremediable; for justice and punishment are kinds of remedies. <milestone unit="section" n="3" />And if the sufferer, having been wronged, has
					inflicted some terrible injury upon himself, the guilty person deserves greater
					punishment; wherefore Sophocles,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">An orator,
						not the tragic poet.</note> when pleading on behalf of Euctemon, who had
					committed suicide after the outrage he had suffered, <pb ed="Bekker" n="1375a" /><lb ed="Bekker" n="1" />declared that he would not assess the punishment at
					less than the victim had assessed it for himself. <milestone unit="section" n="4" />A wrong act is also greater when it is unprecedented, or the first of
					its kind, or when committed with the aid of few accomplices<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">“Or has been seldom paralleled”
						（Cope, but cp. 1.9.38）.</note>; and when it has been
					frequently committed; or when because of it new prohibitions and penalties have
					been sought and found: thus, at <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>
					the citizen owing to whom a new law has been passed, is punished, as well as
					those on whose account a new prison had to be built. <milestone unit="section" n="5" />The crime is greater, the more brutal it is; or when it has been for
					a long time premeditated; when the recital of it inspires terror rather than
					pity. Rhetorical tricks of the following kind may be used:—the
					statement that the accused person has swept away or violated several principles
					of justice, for example, oaths, pledges of friendship, plighted word, the
					sanctity of marriage; for this amounts to heaping crime upon crime. <milestone unit="section" n="6" />Wrong acts are greater when committed in the very
					place where wrongdoers themselves are sentenced, as is done by false witnesses;
					for where would a man not commit wrong, if he does so in a court of justice?
					They are also greater when accompanied by the greatest disgrace; when committed
					against one who has been the guilty person's benefactor, for in that case, the
					wrongdoer is guilty of wrong twice over, in that he not only does wrong, but
					does not return good for good. <milestone unit="section" n="7" />So too, again,
					when a man offends against the unwritten laws of right, for there is greater
					merit in doing right without being compelled<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">And therefore the violation of them is more discreditable.</note>; now the
					written laws involve compulsion, the unwritten do not. Looked at in another way,
					wrongdoing is greater, if it violates the written laws; for a man who commits
					wrongs that alarm him<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">When he thinks of the
						punishment they may entail.</note> and involve punishment, will be ready to
					commit wrong<lb ed="Bekker" n="20" />for which he will not be punished. Let this
					suffice for the treatment of the greater or less degree of wrongdoing.</p>
				<p /></div1></body></text></TEI.2>