<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text lang="en"><body><div1 n="1" type="book" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p><milestone unit="chapter" n="8" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" />These are
					nearly all the topics from which arguments<lb ed="Bekker" n="20" />may be drawn
					in persuading and dissuading; but the most important and effective of all the
					means of persuasion and good counsel is to know all the forms of government and
					to distinguish the manners and customs, institutions, and interests of each;
					<milestone unit="section" n="2" />for all men are guided by considerations of
					expediency, and that which preserves the State is expedient. Further, the
					declaration of the authority is authoritative,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The pronouncements of the supreme authority are themselves authoritative as
						laying down laws and regulations for the citizens.</note> and the different
					kinds of authority are distinguished according to forms of government; in fact,
					there are as many authorities as there are forms of government.</p>
				<p><milestone unit="section" n="3" />Now, there are four kinds of government,
					democracy, oligarchy, aristocracy, monarchy, so that the supreme and deciding
					authority is always a part or the whole of these. <milestone unit="section" n="4" />Democracy is a form of government in which the offices are
					distributed by the people among themselves by lot; in an oligarchy, by those who
					possess a certain property-qualification; in an aristocracy, by those who
					possess an educational qualification, meaning an education that is laid down by
					the law. In fact, in an aristocracy, power and office are in the hands of those
					who have remained faithful to what the law prescribes, and who must of necessity
					appear best, whence this form of government has taken its name. In a monarchy,
					as its name indicates, one man alone is supreme over all; <pb ed="Bekker" n="1366a" /><lb ed="Bekker" n="1" />if it is subject to certain regulations,
					it is called a kingdom; if it is unlimited, a tyranny.</p>
				<p><milestone unit="section" n="5" />Nor should the end of each form of government be
					neglected, for men choose the things which have reference to the end. Now, the
					end of democracy is liberty, of oligarchy wealth, of aristocracy things relating
					to education and what the law prescribes, . . . ,<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">The “end” of monarchy is wanting
						here.</note> of tyranny self-protection. It is clear then that we must
					distinguish the manners and customs, institutions, and interests of each form of
					government, since it is in reference to this that men make their choice.
					<milestone unit="section" n="6" />But as proofs are established not only by
					demonstrative, but also by ethical argument—since we have confidence
					in an orator who exhibits certain qualities, such as goodness, goodwill, or
					both—it follows that we ought to be acquainted with the characters of
					each form of government; for, in reference to each, the character most likely to
					persuade must be that which is characteristic of it. These characters will be
					understood by the same means; for characters reveal themselves in accordance
					with moral purpose, and moral purpose has reference to the end.</p>
				<p><milestone unit="section" n="7" />We have now stated what things, whether future
					or present, should be the aim of those who recommend a certain course; from what
					topics they should derive their proofs of expediency; further, the ways and
					means of being well equipped for dealing with the characters and institutions<lb ed="Bekker" n="20" />of each form of government, so far as was within the
					scope of the present occasion; for the subject has been discussed in detail in
					the <title>Politics</title>.<note resp="Freese" anchored="yes" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Aristot. Pol. 3.1282b" default="NO" valid="yes">Aristot. Pol. 3.7</bibl>.</note></p>
				<p /></div1></body></text></TEI.2>